<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A farther impartial account of the actions of the Inniskilling-men containing the reasons of their first rising, their declarations, oaths, and correspondencies with several parts of the kingdom : together with many other remarkable passages of their behaviour and management, not yet published / written by Capt. William Mc-Carmick, one of the first that took up arms in Inniskilling, for the defence of that place, and the Protestant interest.</title>
            <author>McCarmick, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11414</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13118661</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13118661</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97788</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50168)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97788)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 427:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A farther impartial account of the actions of the Inniskilling-men containing the reasons of their first rising, their declarations, oaths, and correspondencies with several parts of the kingdom : together with many other remarkable passages of their behaviour and management, not yet published / written by Capt. William Mc-Carmick, one of the first that took up arms in Inniskilling, for the defence of that place, and the Protestant interest.</title>
                  <author>McCarmick, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half title: A farther account of the actions of the Inniskilling-men.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1688-1689.</term>
               <term>Enniskillen (Northern Ireland)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:97788:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97788:1"/>
            <p>A FARTHER ACCOUNT OF The ACTIONS OF THE INNISKILLING-MEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:97788:2"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> 17. 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97788:2"/>
            <p>A FARTHER IMPARTIAL ACCOUNT OF THE ACTIONS OF THE <hi>Inniskilling-men.</hi> CONTAINING The REASONS of Their Firſt RISING: Their Declarations, Oaths, and Correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies with ſeveral Parts of the Kingdom. Together with many other Remarkable Paſſages of Their Behaviour and Management, not yet Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>Written by Capt. WILLIAM M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>-CARMICK, One of the firſt that took up Arms in <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> for the Defence of that Place, and the Proteſtant Intereſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97788:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97788:3"/>
            <head>A TRUE AND IMPARTIAL ACCOUNT OF THE ACTIONS OF THE <hi>Inniskilling-men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> DO Proteſt, That I in no ways under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this with a deſign of Reflecting upon Mr. <hi>Andrew Hamilton</hi> (who hath writ on this Subject before), he being a Gentleman that I have, and ever had a very great eſteem for; my whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention being only to make the truth of ſome things appear, that either hath ſlipt Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s memory; or that he hath not been rightly informed in.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of <hi>December,</hi> 1688, we were alarmed, as moſt of the Proteſtants of the Kingdom were, by a Letter ſent us from the Earl of <hi>Mount-Alexander,</hi> directed to him from an unknown hand, acquainting him, That there was a Deſign of a general Maſſacre of the Proteſtants, Man, Woman, and Child, throughout the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be Acted by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts and their Adherents, the Ninth Day of the ſaid Month: This Letter, what its operation was in other Places, I know not; but it made ſo deep an impreſſion on the minds of moſt in and about <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> (the Cruelties of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97788:4"/>the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in <hi>Forty one,</hi> being yet freſh in many of their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories) that ſeveral of the Countrey ſent in their beſt Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Furniture and Papers to <hi>Iniskilling;</hi> thinking them more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure there, than with themſelves: And we obſerving that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were gathering themſelves together on all hands in great Numbers, having for a long time before employed all the Smiths of their ſort, in making Skeens (<hi>viz.</hi> a kind of ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Baggonets) and Pike-heads, wherewith to Arm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves privately; we were ſtruck into great Conſternation; but reſolved not to have our Throats Cut aſleep, the moſt of the Townſmen the Day and Night of the deſigned Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, keeping ſtrict Guards with what ſort of Weapons they had; and there being a <hi>Friary</hi> then in Town, one <hi>Anthony Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Guardian of the <hi>Friary,</hi> a Cunning, Subtil Felow, making his remarks of our keeping Guards, went out of Town in the Morning, about Four Miles, where a Multitude of his ſort met him, to hear a Sermon as they alledged; where in the end of his Diſcourſe, he acquainted his Hearers, that <hi>Innis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing</hi>-Men were taking up Arms, and going to Rebel; that he ſee a great many of them in Arms in the Streets that Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Headed by one <hi>Mac-Carmick,</hi> a great Rebel, as he termed him, but he hoped ere long to make them quiet enough. Several of the Friars being afraid, ſlipt out of Town; but this Impudent Guardian ſtayed, and did not ſtick to ſay, That he would have a Red Croſs very ſoon, at every door in Town. And truly I believe was inſtrumental, in cauſing two Foot Companies of Soldiers, <hi>viz.</hi> Capt. <hi>Nugents,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Shirlo's,</hi> belonging to Sir <hi>Thomas Nucoman's</hi> Regiment, to be ſent to Gariſon upon us: But as the great Providence of God would have it, our Provoſt (that's the Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in Town) the ſecond day after the Maſſacre ſhould have been committed, received a Letter by the Lord <hi>Tyrcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi>'s directions, then Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> from Secretary <hi>Ellice,</hi> ordering him to provide Quarters for two Foot-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies. A thing never practicable before, to ſend Orders
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97788:4"/>for providing of Quarters, ere the men that were to Quarter, ſhewed their Patent. But had it not been for this, theſe Two Companies had been in our Town, ere we had known of their March. But this ſtruck deep upon our ſpirits; we did then begin to conſider the dangerous condition we were in, and did think it high time to uſe our diligence in endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, as well as our Lives; it being either already, or ſuddenly like to be, cruſhed in moſt Parts of the Kingdom; therefore reſolved (if poſſible) to ſupport it in that Corner.</p>
            <p>The Townſmen upon this, were called together, where it was debated, Whether we ſhould refuſe entrance to the two Companies, or not; there were various opinions, both Arms and Ammunition being wanting; but in the general, it was thought adviſable to conſult one Capt. <hi>James Corry,</hi> a very leading-Gentleman in that County, in this ſo weighty an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, he living within a ſmall Mile of the Town. But he not willing to countenance us in this, neither to aſſiſt us with his Advice, we again aſſemble our ſelves; but being ſtill divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Opinion, we could conclude on nothing.</p>
            <p>There was one <hi>William Browning, Robert Clark,</hi> and <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Mac-Carmick,</hi> got privately into a Back Room, where came to them <hi>James Euart,</hi> and <hi>Allen Cuſhcart.</hi> Theſe Five reſolved, in ſpite of all oppoſition, to deny entrance to theſe two Companies of Soldiers, and defend the Town with their Lives: To that purpoſe diſpatched Expreſſes, in name of the Townſmen, about midnight, to moſt of the Gentlemen of the Country, acquainting them of their Reſolution, and deſiring their Aſſiſtance; and that they would give us timely notice which Road the Soldiers Marched, that we might put our ſelves in a poſture of receiving them. In the mean time <hi>Mac-Carmick</hi> gets Timber brought into Town, and ſets Carpenters a work to get up the Draw-Bridg upon the Eaſt-end of the Town; the Bridge being newly built of Stone, and the Draw not put up.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97788:5"/>
            <p>Next Night, about Midnight, came an Expreſs from <hi>Danid Eccles</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> with this following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PAſſing all Complements of Thanks; We are ſo aſſured that two Companies of Foot are Marching to</hi> Inniskilling, <hi>that Capt.</hi> Nugent, <hi>with other Officers, are in</hi> Clowniſh <hi>this night on their March thither; but as for their Soldiers, though they were expected there, it's thought they will go by</hi> Newtown-Butler, <hi>and it's ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed they are in</hi> Drum. <hi>We Pray God bleſs you, and can only tell you, That a Troop of Dragoons came to</hi> Ardmagh <hi>Saturday laſt, where the Inhabitants offered them Candle, Fire, and Salt; ſo that if they expected any further neceſſaries, they were to pay before-hand; whereupon the Lieutenant Marched to his Capt. Coll.</hi> Bryan, Mac-Maghow <hi>at</hi> Charlemont, <hi>and the Townſmen went to Church with their Arms, of which two Centinels were placed on the Steeple, to Pire their Firelacks, and Ring the Bells, as a ſignal to the Countrey, if they had offered any thing ill; of which we had no further ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As to what other things you propoſe, aſſure your ſelves, we ſhall be as ready to offer all Teſtimony of Friendſhip, as may be expected from ſuch as are not wanting to pray for you; and are expecting a particalar Correſpondence from you, as you ſhall have from us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <trailer>To Mr. <hi>William M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>-Carmick</hi> at <hi>Inniskilling.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This came no ſooner to hand, than <hi>Mac-Carmick</hi> went to the Provoſt, and ſome others of the Townſmen, intreating them as ſoon as Day appear'd, to ſet the Carpenters again to work at the Draw-Bridge, getting a Horſeback himſelf, and Rides immediately to Cornet <hi>Guſtavus Hamilton,</hi> a Gentleman that liv'd on the Weſt ſide of the Town, in the Barony of <hi>Maghre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy,</hi> about five Mile from the Town, to know his and the other Neighbouring-Gentlemens Reſolutions; who were all very ready and willing to joyn in the Defence of <hi>Inniskilling;</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97788:5"/>of them, together with Cornet <hi>Hamilton,</hi> coming into Town with M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> 
               <hi>Carmick,</hi> but upon the way were met by an Expreſs from the Provoſt, with this following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MR. Latournall <hi>came juſt now from Captain</hi> Corry, <hi>and in his coming into the Town, commanded the Carpenters to leave off working at the Drawbridg, and alſo came to me and begged I ſhould ſend for my Brethren, and diſſwade them from the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of denying the Soldiers Entrance, and to provide them Quarters as ſpeedily as I could. My requeſt to you is, That you will immediately give the Gentlemen in theſe parts an Accompt of my deſign, which is to give them entrance, and that you will make all the haſte you can home to aſſiſt me, is all from</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> 
                        <date>Dec. 13th. 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Yours to ſerve you whilſt I am, <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L DANE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>
                     <hi>To Mr.</hi> William M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>-Carmick, <hi>Theſe.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>By this you may ſee how ſtrangely mens minds were hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and what a hard task it was to unite a divided multitude; yet this Letter hindered not our coming into Town, where Captain <hi>Corry,</hi> and ſeveral other Gentlemen, livers on the Eaſt ſide of <hi>Loghearne,</hi> were aſſembled. Things again were deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but moſt were for admitting the two Companies, alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtrength of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in that Country, they being well armed and provided in Ammunition, having all the Arms, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines and Gariſons of the Kingdom in their hands, ſave <hi>Londonderry;</hi> we wanting both Arms and Ammunition, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Soldiers amongſt us, and the uncertainty of a headſtrong multitude, being likely that they would as ſoon throw down their Arms as they took them up, when they either ſee an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or were reduced to any hardſhips or want; yet all could not do, the Townſmen with the Gentlemen that came out of the Barony of <hi>Maghreboy,</hi> ſtood firm to the Reſolution of neither
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97788:6"/>ſubmitting themſelves to be ſlaves, nor to aſſiſt the making of others ſo; <hi>Carpenters</hi> were ſet to work again at the Bridge. And indeed though Captain <hi>Corry</hi> would not at all comply with our Reſolution, yet when we ſent for the Chains and Irons that had formerly belonged to the Bridge, he ſent them in to us; we ſoon got up the Draw-bridge, and again ſent to all the Neighbourhood, intreating them to joyn with us both for their own preſervation and ours, promiſing them free quarter in Town both for themſelves and Horſes; upon this ſeveral of the Country came in, being thereunto much incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by the induſtrious ſolicitation of one Mr. <hi>Kelſy</hi> a Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt Miniſter, who indeed laboured both publickly and privately, in animating his hearers to take up Arms, and ſtand upon their own defence, ſhewing example himſelf, by wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arms, and marching in the head of them, when toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Our next Care was to turn all Papiſts out of Town, ſeizing <hi>Anthony Murry</hi> the forenamed Friar-Guardian, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to the Caſtle, where he continued Priſoner a good while, and after by a Rope made his Eſcape over the Wall, ſo got off in a Boat; but although the Rope ſet him at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then, yet it may ſend him to another world ere long.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> the 15th of <hi>December,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Baird</hi> and Mr. <hi>James Johnſton</hi> were ſent on Horſeback to view and bring intelligence of the Enemies approach, who return'd upon <hi>Sunday</hi> about Ten of the Clock, with aſſurance of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies being within four or five miles of the Town; moſt of the Inhabitants being in Church, got immediately to their Arms; our number not two hundred Foot, and they not near half Armed; our Horſe about 150. ſuch as they were; who took the field with a reſolution to fall in upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Reer, if they had offered to enter the Town by force; but they coming within a mile, and meeting ſeveral of their own ſort that were turn'd out of Town, acquainting them that we were reſolved to fight, and indeed magnifying our num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97788:6"/>the Soldiers were ſo diſcouraged, that they immediately Retreated, the moſt of their Officers being at Dinner in Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Corry</hi>'s; upon intelligence of which our Horſe, with three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Firelooks purſued them; their Officers perceiving our Horſe to move towards them, fled likewiſe after their men; we hearing that they had ſeveral Horſe-loads of ſpare Arms, and Ammunition good ſtore along with them for arming the Country, were reſolved to have them, theſe being the chief things we wanted; but our Horſe being met by Captain <hi>Corry,</hi> were perſwaded to return, to the great diſſatisfaction of the Foot; he having, as we were told, paſt his word for the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſafety while they were in our Country; they marched that night to M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> 
               <hi>Guiers</hi> Bridge, eight miles from us, and there ſtood upon their Guard all night, next day to <hi>Newtown Buttler,</hi> where in the night time they had like to have ſeiſed three Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of ours that we ſent to obſerve their motion, and to know if any of the Country joyned them, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>William Browning,</hi> Mr. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and Mr. <hi>James Corry,</hi> who lighting in their Quarters, and aſſuming other Names, after finding out their number, ſtrength, and reſolution, having diſcourſed ſeveral of their Officers, were diſcovered to be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niskilling</hi> men; and ere they could well mount their Horſes, were ſurrounded by a ſtrong Guard of the Enemy; but our men made their way through them, and eſcaped to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Cavan,</hi> where they ſtayed in Captain <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s, while the two Companies marched paſt them to <hi>Cavan,</hi> then return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the two Companies ſtayed ſome ſmall time in <hi>Cavan,</hi> then marched to <hi>Firmah,</hi> twelve miles further, being alarmed that the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> men were coming to diſarm them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guſtavus Hamilton</hi> during their being near the Town, kept at a place called <hi>Portoragh,</hi> within a quarter of a mile of the Town, with near a hundred Horſe, to ſupport and aſſiſt the Townſmen if any force had been offered them by the two Companies; but as for carrying meat or drink out of Town to treat them, or ſending any of our number to perſwade
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97788:7"/>them to return, there was no ſuch thing; it's true indeed, they did not ſhew their Patent, nor once deſire to be admitted into Town.</p>
            <p>After this, we always kept ſtrict Guards; and being ſenſible that a Body without a Head ſeldom lives long, our next care was to make choice of ſome Gentleman to Command us, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> indeed every day growing more inſolent than uſual, and gathering themſelves together in Companies, Exerciſing, and learning to handle their Arms; yea, and taking away the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants Cattel both publickly and privately; nay more, they were grown to that height of Impudence, that upon the 16th. of <hi>December</hi> they took from an honeſt man of the name of <hi>Foſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet,</hi> his Cattel; he followed, and overtaking the men that were driving them away, the Rogues ſeiſed the honeſt man, and in a moſt Barbarous manner ripped up his Belly, and tore out his Inteſtions, and ſo left him; this meaſure in all probability we ſhould have met with, had not the Almighty God put it in our hearts to refuſe a Popiſh Gariſon into our Town.</p>
            <p>The Townſmen Aſſembling themſelves, Sir <hi>Michael Cole,</hi> Proprietor of the Town, being then in <hi>England,</hi> made choice of <hi>Guſtavus Hamilton</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> to be our Governour, a Gentleman ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well deſcended, and one reputed to be of juſt and good Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels; but ere this Election, or his coming to take the charge upon him, we had a Randezvous of all the Country that would joyn with us, upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 20th. where came Sir <hi>Gerard Ervin</hi> and the forenamed Captain <hi>Corry,</hi> and ſeeing Mr. <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Browning</hi> coming into Town in the head of a party of Horſe, they cauſed him to be ſeiſed, and was writing his <hi>Mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus</hi> to ſend him to Goal, for appearing in Arms, thinking by this to fright us from our Reſolution of holding out the Town; but we ſoon ſet him at liberty, and ſent in one Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>Smith,</hi> an ancient Gentleman, and Juſtice of Peace in the County, to Sir <hi>Gerard</hi> and Captain <hi>Corry,</hi> to tell them, that we took it unkindly their offering to ſecure any of our number, or to fright or deject the ſpirits of thoſe that were willing to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97788:7"/>joyn in defence of their Lives and Religion; deſiring them immediately to leave the Town, and give us no farther trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, elſe we muſt be forced to ſend them where they were a ſending Mr. <hi>Browning;</hi> this Meſſage ſtartled them; they called Quarters, and immediately took their Horſes, and left the Town; yet Captain <hi>Corry</hi> made it his buſineſs after, to hinder his Tenants, or any other he had influence upon, to joyn with us; but we were not long troubled with him, for he left the Kingdom the <hi>March</hi> following.</p>
            <p>This was not the only diſcouragement we met with; for Mr. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> , a Servant of Sir <hi>Michael Coles,</hi> whoſe Town <hi>Inniskilling</hi> is, dwelling at that time in Sir <hi>Michael</hi>'s Caſtle, the only ſtrength of the Town, refuſed us entrance into it, or to deliver it, or any of the Arms in it up to us, while Mr. <hi>Henry Smith,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Malcome Cathcart,</hi> both Captains in the Army ſince, took it by ſurprize; ſo we got poſſeſſion, and kept a ſtrong Guard in it ever after.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all Difficulties and oppoſition we met with, we ſtood firm to our firſt intention, and <hi>Guſtavus Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> being, as I ſaid before, elected our Governour, he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced it, and removing his Family, came into <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to live.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing he did, calling the Towns-men together, he thought it adviſable (<hi>Londonderry</hi> at that time likewiſe hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out, having refuſed entrance to the Lord <hi>Antrim</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to ſettle a true Correſpondence betwixt <hi>Derry</hi> and us, and likewiſe to know, if poſſible, my Lord <hi>Mountjoy</hi>'s Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations towards us; and to procure ſome Arms and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Derry;</hi> to which purpoſe Mr. <hi>Allen Cathcart,</hi> and Mr. <hi>William M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>.-Carmick</hi> were ſent; but ere they got the length of <hi>Londonderry,</hi> they had capitulated with Lord <hi>Mountjoy,</hi> and admitted ſix Companies of his Regiment into their City, what Papiſts were in the ſaid Companies being firſt turn'd out; we were very kindly receiv'd by the Citizens, they promiſing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97788:8"/>us help of Ammunition and Arms, and to bear a true and conſtant Correſpondence with us, as we promiſed to them. Then our Meſſengers returning, deliver this following Letter to my Lord <hi>Mountjoy</hi> at <hi>Newtownſtewart.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOVR Lordſhip cannot but know what dreadful Apprehenſions we were ſtruck with, when from ſeveral parts of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom we received the ſad Account of a deſigned Maſſacre of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; in the midſt of which fears, to heighten our ſorrows, we had news of two Companies of Foot, all Papiſts, ordered to gariſon upon us; and further, to deject our deſpairing Spirits, the Threats of the Officers of theſe Companies, of treading us in the Kennels, and dragging of our Inteſtins about the Streets, was aſſured us; nay more, my Lord, the frequent aſſembling of the</hi> Iriſh <hi>in great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies on all hands of us, their reſtleſs pains in making Skeins and Pikes; inſomuch, that a man, and he of a mean Fortune, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers'd in one Week threeſcore; and having likewiſe the intelligence of your Lordſhip's being confined, for only deſiring that the Proteſtants might have liberty to buy Arms for their own defence, did create in us ſo great fear, that we could not propoſe ſafety, or the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our lives in any humane probability, but by refuſing theſe two Companies entrance into our Town. My Lord, our Reſolutions are firm and fully fixed to preſerve this Place, as a Refuge for many Souls to fly to, if any Maſſacre ſhould be attempted, which we daily fear and tremble to think of.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe things ſeriouſly conſidered, and ſeeing ſo great and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Dangers hovering over our heads, we can do no leſs than una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly reſolve not to admit any Popiſh Gariſon here; which we hope your Lordſhip will repreſent favourably to the Government; We return very humble and hearty thanks for your kind and prudent Meſſage by Mr.</hi> Marvin, <hi>and do aſſure your Lordſhip, That we will demean our ſelves with all the ſobriety imaginable; neither did it ever enter into our thoughts, to ſpill one drop of Blood (unleſs we be thereunto forced in our own defence) or to take from any man
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97788:8"/>the value of one Farthing; which we intreat your Lordſhip to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve from,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Decemb.</hi> 21. 1681.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>My LORD,</salute>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt Humble and Obedient Servants, <hi>The Inhabitants of</hi> Inniskilling.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>My Lord, after peruſing this Letter, enquired what ſtrength we might be of; and being anſwered, he ſaid, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Gariſon of the King's Soldiers. <hi>M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>-Carmick</hi> replied, That we knew not how far that could conſiſt with our ſafety, or the general preſervation of the Proteſtant Intereſt in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter; Inniskilling</hi> being the only Inlet from <hi>Connought</hi> to that Province, from whence they would as an Inundation overflow our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and they having no other Paſs for above Forty Miles over <hi>Longhearne,</hi> we did believe we could not in any way be ſecure, if we admitted a Popiſh Gariſon there. My Lord anſwered, the King will protect you. But Mr. <hi>Cathcart</hi> ſharply replied, that he could not protect himſelf; At which my Lord turn'd, and walked a good while without ſpeaking; then told us, That we might return home, and deſired, that his Service might be given to our Towns-men, whom he would come and converſe with on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> following; in the mean time intreated, that we might be cautious of falling into blood; which we promiſed, and ſo parted; but in place of my Lord's coming according to his promiſe, he ſent Mr. <hi>Marvin</hi> to excuſe him; he going to <hi>Dublin</hi> (being ſent for by <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>) and ſo into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the Return of our Meſſengers, we began to form Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, Captain <hi>Allen Cathcart, William M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>-Carmick</hi> his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Ralph Picking</hi> Enſign, raiſing the firſt; and Captain <hi>Malcome Cathcart,</hi> the ſecond, (moſt conſiſting of Nonconformiſts, as they term them; that party effectually eſpouſing our intereſt, and never declined us in the moſt dangerous times.) The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97788:9"/>a Company of Foot in the Country, where he had lived, and a Troop of Horſe in and about the Town.</p>
            <p>At this time We were put to great toil, in breaking the Ice round our Town every Day; it ſtanding in an Iſland, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no other Walls ſave the Water, which Froſe ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly up, that Both Foot and Horſe might March over it with ſafety.</p>
            <p>Toward the latter end of <hi>December,</hi> we had an Expreſs from my Lord <hi>Blany,</hi> with advice, not raſhly to admira Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Papiſts into our Town, but rather to continue in the condition we were in, while we knew what meaſures were taken by the Nobility and Gentry of the Counties of <hi>Antrim, Down, Ardmagh,</hi> and <hi>Managhan,</hi> and a Letter incloſed, ſent to his Lordſhip from <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> which was this.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE herewith ſend you a Copy of the Capitulation betwixt Lord</hi> Mountjoy, <hi>and the City of</hi> Derry: <hi>Whereupon that Place was put into the hands of Lieutenant-Collonel</hi> Lundy: <hi>We alſo ſend your Lordſhip a Narrative of what paſt betwixt my Lord</hi> Mountjoy <hi>and a Gentleman we intruſted from hence, to manage both with his Lordſhip and the City; by all which your Lordſhip may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that Lord</hi> Mountjoy <hi>propoſeth managing the Proteſtant Intereſt by leſs hazardous means than was intended: And we are unwilling to ſuſpect his Lordſhip's ſincerity, and think it may be prejudicial to us as yet to thwart his Lordſhip; whereupon we think it moſt adviſeable for us, to defer putting any thing in execution, till a new notice is given; and that in the mean time we may take care that his Lordſhip be diſcourſed herein; and we thereby judge what are the meaſures moſt proper for us to purſue. We believe your Lordſhip hath wrote to Lord</hi> Granard, <hi>and Lord</hi> Kingſton; <hi>and we now deſire that you will, with the utmost ſpeed, give them and other our Friends intimation of this our altering our reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with the motives thereunto; we alſo deſire that you would acquaint Lord</hi> Granard, <hi>that we do however rely ſo much on him,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97788:9"/>that if he judges our method beſt, and either hath or will make any ſtep towards countenancing thereof, ſo as to think his Honour in the leaſt ingaged, that we will all unanimouſly ſtand by him. Your Lordſhip perceives, that it is likewiſe intended, that</hi> Inniskilling <hi>ſubmit as</hi> Derry <hi>hath done; we refer it to your Lordſhip, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if means ought to be uſed, that they at leaſt delay ſo doing: and for your Lordſhip to Act therein, or Prevent it, as you think fit, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Belfaſt</hi> 
                        <date>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 26.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>You ſee by this, it was concluded, That the Holding out <hi>Inniskilling</hi> was thought convenient, and indeed we had firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved it; but wanting Ammunition, Arms and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, we in <hi>January</hi> ſent Mr. <hi>Hugh Hamilton,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Allen Cathcart</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> with an Addreſs to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> hearing King <hi>James</hi> had left that Kingdom: And in their way to <hi>Donoghadee</hi> (where they were to take Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for <hi>Scotland,</hi> toward their more ſecure paſſage) to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe the Lords and Gentlemen of the North-Eaſt; to whom we wrote this following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHILST we and all the Proteſtants of this Kingdom, groaned under the fear of approaching Miſery; and there was nothing, but an univerſal dread of eminent Ruin ſuggeſted to our thoughts, and that we ſee our Religion, our Laws, Liberties, Lives, and our all at ſtake, ſo that nothing could be added to our danger, but our willingneſs to lye under whatſoever was impoſed upon us; the Law of Self-preſervation (one of the Ancienteſt of the World) conſtrained us, rather to chuſe an hazardous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, than a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Slavery; to which we were the more provoked, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting Menaces of thoſe, who under pretence of Quartering upon us, came to Pillage us, and deſigned to make this their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to the Devaſtation of this part of the Province. So that not being willing to be inſlaved, and help to make others ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97788:10"/>too, this Paſs being the only Inlet from</hi> Conagh <hi>to</hi> Ulſter, <hi>from whence, as by an Inundation, it muſt have been overflowed; we ſtand upon our Guard, and do reſolve by the bleſſing of God, rather to meet our Danger, than expect it. We doubt not, but your own Conſiderations hath ſuggeſted thoughts of this Nature to you alſo, which we do believe may induce you to a neceſſary Defence of your Selves and Neighbours; and therefore do humby intreat your can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and ſincere advice in the management of this great Affair, which is too weighty for our weak Shoulders to bear alone, ſince we are ſure to be the firſt that ſhall meet with the dangerous, and highly incenſed, revengful Hands of our Enemies; our great hope is, That God will incline you to our Aſſiſtance, and give us Courage and Succeſs in this ſo juſt an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking; we intreat Credit may be given to our Meſſengers, who are well-acquainted with the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of thoſe that ſhall not fail to continue</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>To the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Mount-Alexander,</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Maſſarine,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Reiden,</hi> or any of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Faithful Humble Servants <hi>Guſtavus Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton,</hi> and the reſt of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Innikilling.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>We had a very kind and favourable return to this Letter, from the Honourable Perſons it was ſent too; we now dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently applied our ſelves in raiſing more men, Capt. <hi>Rob. Clark,</hi> Capt. <hi>Will. Browning,</hi> Capt. <hi>Alex. Archiſon,</hi> Capt. <hi>Robert Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venſon,</hi> Capt. <hi>Robert Corry,</hi> Capt. <hi>Hen. Smith,</hi> Capt. <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald Hamilton,</hi> each raiſing a Company; Sir <hi>John Hume</hi> who indeed did from the beginning effectually eſpouſe our Intereſt, raiſed and armed two Foot Companies, and a good Troop of Horſe; joyning always with us, when occaſion; Fortified and Victualled his own Houſe, ſo that it was capable of contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and maintaining a very conſiderable Gariſon; and ſent into <hi>England</hi> for his Eldeſt Son, who had been formerly in the Army there, a very hopeful young Gentleman, who headed his Horſe: This Garriſon was no ſmall ſupport to <hi>Inniskilling;</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:97788:10"/>it lying three miles below the Town, on <hi>Conaught</hi> ſide of the River, and a great defence to the Country about it.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of <hi>January</hi> we received a Letter ſent us by Mr. <hi>Charles Leſly</hi> from <hi>Glaslough,</hi> a place in the County of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naghan</hi> where he lived, it was in Characters, and ſhew'd the Intentions of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Prieſts and Friars, whoſe reſtleſs ſpirits left nothing unattempted to drive on their Helliſh deſigns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the poor Proteſtants: The Letter was thus,
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>M17t27 McK2nn1,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>945r S2lf2 t4g2th2r 553th R4b2rt &amp; 34hn 7t51rt c1pti3n 453nd4n 553ll31m 224rth 1r2 15th4r3726 89 92 c45nc2ll 4f 658l341 t4 72372 5p4n ch1rl2s l27l32 1n6 34hn kn4k7, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t3ne 34hnſt4n, th2r2 1r2 1ll74 74m2 c4ntr3526 6273gn7 li36 3n pr1ct37 t4 75rpr372 92ch5rch22 4f 1rdm1gh l5rg1nl37n|1g1r592 &amp; 18452 4n 7c4r2 4f 92 pr3nc3p1ll Chr5ch27 4f 3r2l1n6 &amp; all 92 pr274n2r7 1r2 t4 82 71f2 k2pt 543ll f5rth2r 4r62r7 h45 252r g2ntl2m2n 915 1r2 t4 72171 1ll 3n gl17|l45gh Ch5rch pr27n2r7 &amp; r1372 5p 1ll 92 tr5gh t4945r 1737t|1n72 th2r24f 945 m57tn44 f13l2, 17 945 553ll 1n7552r2 3t 53th 92 l472 4f 945r l3527 3f 252r 9<hi rend="sup">2</hi> 554rl6 t5rn7 17 3t 553ll 3f 92 p4p2 c1n 72n6 57 1n 1rm32.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Fr2611th <date>62c2m82r 92 26.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>F1th2r G1rl2n. F1th2r 61l9.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>This Letter was intercepted by Sir <hi>Nicholas Achiſon,</hi> and ſent by him to <hi>Mr. Leſsly,</hi> from whom we had it wrote over thus:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>Mr. M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
                           </hi> Kenna,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>YOur ſelf, together with</hi> Robert <hi>and</hi> John Steward, <hi>Captain</hi> Ovindon, William Betagh, <hi>are Authorized by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of</hi> Dublin <hi>to ſeize upon</hi> Charles Leſly, <hi>and</hi> John Knocks, <hi>Captain</hi> Johnſon; <hi>there are alſo ſome contrived deſigns laid in practiſe to ſurprize the Churches of</hi> Ardmagh, Lurgan, Liſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garvy,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97788:11"/>
                        <hi>and above one ſcore of the principal Churches of</hi> Ireland; <hi>and all the Priſoners are to be kept while further orders: However Gentlemen, you are to ſeize all in</hi> Glaſlough <hi>Church Priſoners; and raiſe up all the</hi> Trugh <hi>to your aſſiſtance; thereof you muſt not fail as you will anſwer it with the loſs of your lives, if ever the world turn, as it will if the Pope can ſend us an Army.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Tredagh <date>
                              <hi>Dec.</hi> the 26.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Father Garland. Father Daly.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>About this time came another to us out of <hi>Conaught</hi> in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE occaſion of this trouble to you, is to tell you, That we have undoubted and repeated advice, that many hundreds of men, Foot and Dragoons, are Arming themſelves in the County of</hi> Ruſcommon <hi>and</hi> Mayo, <hi>with an intent to fall upon our Friends in</hi> Boyle, <hi>and this County; and conſequently purſue their deſign down towards you. We have therefore agreed unanimouſly to ſecure this Town, and bring in the Country people to our aid, but before we ſtir in what we have ſaid, there is a party of fifty or ſixty to go hence; who are to joyn in the County of</hi> Roſcommon, <hi>with ſome more to be commanded by Captain</hi> Coot, <hi>upon a very important deſign, which if pleaſe God may be effected, will be of great conſequence to us all, and of no ſmall diſadvantage to our Enemies, that if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is to be done within two or three days; now it is the deſire of Captain</hi> Coot, <hi>that all, or as many of the Proteſtants as may unite, may gather into</hi> Balliſhanan, <hi>and</hi> Dunnigall, <hi>where you may be in a readineſs not only to ſecure your ſelves againſt the</hi> Blow <hi>that is deſigned to be given, but alſo to be in a condition to relieve us, if by the multitude we be oppreſſed: Matters are come to a great height in our neighbouring Counties, there being no leſs then</hi> 24 <hi>Captains in one Barony in the County of</hi> Mayo; <hi>therefore as you tender your welfare, ſlight not this matter, communicate it with all prudence to Mr.</hi> Folliat, <hi>Mr.</hi> Whitway, <hi>Lieutenant</hi> Smith, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Atkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97788:11"/>
                     <hi>and the reſt of your Friends: What elſe is done here you ſhall know it; we hope to have all done by</hi> Thurſday, <hi>for we find time is not to be ſlipt; Lord</hi> Kingſtone <hi>and Captain</hi> Coot <hi>comes hither; it's their deſire that you ſhould ſend an Expreſs immediately to</hi> Derry <hi>to know if we may have any help of Arms and Ammunition from thence, for it is the only thing we lack, when at the ſame time our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies are well ſtored. Pray deſire your Friends to tell what quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Arms we may expect, and the ſorts, and how much Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we may immediately ſend for them; this deſign is not to be Communicated to any but to thoſe you are ſure of: Lord</hi> Granard <hi>is now in the Country; Lord</hi> Kingſton <hi>went to him yeſterday, and this night or to morrow morning we expect to know how his pulſe beats. Let us know how Matters are with you: We are told</hi> Derry <hi>is ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Sligo, <date>
                           <hi>Decemb.</hi> 27. 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter was directed, to Mr. <hi>John Delap</hi> of <hi>Belliſhannon,</hi> and by him ſent to us: By theſe frequent admonitions from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts, any man may ſee what reaſon we had to ſtand upon our Guard, and yet how we might have been diſcouraged, having neither number ſufficient, Arms, nor Ammunition fit for the Number we had; but God Almighty gave us an Heart with Courage and Reſolution, that ſupplyed all our wants.</p>
            <p>We now every Day wrought hard in Fortifying the Town, making Bulwarks and Rampiers at each place, where the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was fordable; and appointed a certain Number of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, together with Mr. <hi>Kelſey</hi> the Nonconformiſt Miniſter, to ſit in Counſel every Day, to conſider what meaſures were moſt proper to purſue for our Preſervation; the firſt things done, were theſe following orders.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Book to be made, to inſert all Orders that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded upon; and theſe to be Signed by them that were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to take inſpection, and conclude upon matters fit, ſo firmly obeyed by all.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97788:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. That the Country were to do duty, by watching their turns in Town; whereby to ſecure that place as a ſure refuge for them to fly to, if any miſchief ſhould be offered to them by the Natives; and while they were upon Duty, to have free Quarters.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Locks be forthwith Provided for the Bridges, and they to be Locked up at a convenient Hour, and the Keys car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Governour, or to the Captain of the Main Guard, if the Governour ſhould think fit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That Expreſſes be immediately ſent abroad, to engage a True Correſpondence with the Gentlemen in the adjacent Counties, ſo to receive from them frequent Intelligence of their knowledg, or what their Reſolutions or Obſervations were.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That a conſiderable quantity of Proviſions, <hi>viz.</hi> Beef, Butter, Cheeſe, and Meal, be laid up in Store to ſubſiſt the Gariſon, if a Seige ſhould happen; and that the Countrey be encouraged to ſend in, and lay up their Proviſions, of Grain or other things, in Town; fearing leſt it might be ſurprized by the Enemy, and ſo made uſe of againſt us.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That good ſtore of Pikes and Sythes, fixed in long Poles be made ready, and kept in ſtore to Arm all the Countrey, if occaſion were.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That a Horſe-Guard be kept, for ſcouring the Country in the night time, for fear of an Ambuſh or ſudden Attack; and to ſee that the Watches there be duly kept.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That all the Boats and Cotes upon <hi>Longhaven</hi> be ſecured, and brought to the Caſtle of <hi>Inniskilling;</hi> ſo to prevent the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies having the advantage of ſurprizing us by Water.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That all the fire Arms that may be had, together with all the old Muſquet-Barrels that are now in the Caſtle, be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately fixed up, and made fit for Service.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That the four ſmall Braſs Pieces now in the Caſtle, be put upon Carriages, and made fit for Service.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That the Papiſts and Natives of the Countrey, be not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97788:12"/>admitted into Town upon Markets-Days, with Skeens or Half Pikes, neither allowed to ſtay in Town all Night.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That a General Randeſvouz of the Country be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, where liſts may be taken of all that joyn with us, the better to know our ſtrength, and there to be form'd into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies and Troops, Officers made to Command and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline them, and they obliged to obey their Officers.</p>
            <p>Having thus in ſome meaſure preſcribed our ſelves ſome method to walk by, we put the former Orders punctually in execution, every man obſerving what he was Commanded, as duly, as if we had all been under Pay; no man in the leaſt grudging to perform the hardeſt Duty; ſo unanimous we were amongſt our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>James Caldwell</hi> coming about this time to Town, brought with him by Water from <hi>Belturbet,</hi> ſome Gunpowder for the better defence of the Country where he lived, and left us about Sixty Pounds, which we looked upon to be a great matter at that time.</p>
            <p>In <hi>January</hi> alſo came to us from <hi>Conought, Thom is Lloyd,</hi> and <hi>Dan. Hudſon</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> with their Families, both Ingenious Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen; and I may ſay indeed, in a good time for us; for all that we did after, worth taking notice of, was under the Conduct and Command of Mr. <hi>Lloyd;</hi> Mr. <hi>Hudſon</hi> by his ſound and good Advice in Counſel, contributed much to our advantage; we ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more of Mr. <hi>Lloyd</hi> hereafter.</p>
            <p>We likewiſe about this time had ſent us from my Lord <hi>Blany,</hi> by Captain <hi>Thomas Cole,</hi> a Copy of the Proceedings of the Lords of the North Eaſt; the Papers were theſe.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IT being notoriouſly known, not only to the Proteſtants of the Northern Counties, but to thoſe throughout this whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>That the Publick peace of this Nation is now in great and eminent Danger; and that it is abſolutely neceſſary for all Proteſtants to agree within their ſeveral Counties in ſome method, beſides thoſe ordinarily appointed by the Laws, for their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97788:13"/>own defence; and the preſerving as much as in them lies, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace of the Nation, which is ſo much endeavoured to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed by Popiſh and Illegal Counſellors, and their Abettors. And for that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Secreſy, and Diſpatch, are neceſſary to the effecting of the ſaid Deſign: Therefore we the Perſons here under Subſcribing our Names, Do in behalf of our ſelves, and Proteſtant Tenants, Authoriſe and Impower Sir</hi> Arthur Reidon <hi>Baronet, Sir</hi> Robert Colvil, James Hamilton <hi>of</hi> Newcaſtle, John Hawkins, <hi>and</hi> James Hamilton <hi>of</hi> Tullimore <hi>
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> or any three of them, to Aſſemble at ſuch Time and Place, and as oft as they ſhall think fit, and to Conſult, Adviſe, and Determine of all matters which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the Publick Peace of this County and Kingdom. And we the ſaid Perſons hereunto Subſcribing our Names, Proteſtants in the County of</hi> Down, <hi>do hereby engage for our ſelves, and as far as in us lies, our Tenants aforeſaid, To Perform and Execute all ſuch Orders, Commands, and Directions, as ſhall from time to time be made publick, or given by the ſaid Perſons, or any three of them as aforeſaid. In Witneſs whereof we have hereunto Subſcribed our Names, this</hi> 17th. <hi>of</hi> January, 1688.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>In Witneſs of the Acceptance of the above Truſt; we have hereunto put our Hands.</dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>M. J. H. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>A. R.</item>
                           <item>R. C.</item>
                           <item>J. H.</item>
                           <item>J. H.</item>
                           <item>J. H.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97788:13"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>By the Council of Five of the Counties of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trim,</hi> purſuant to a Truſt repoſed in them by the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Gentry of the ſaid Counties.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HAving an intire Confidence of the Conduct, Valour and Fidelity of the Right Honourable</hi> Hugh <hi>Earl of</hi> Mountalexander, <hi>We do hereby impower his Lordſhip to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all ſuch Forces as ſhall from time to time be raiſed by us, and other the Inhabitants of the ſaid Counties of</hi> Down <hi>and</hi> Antrim, <hi>for preſerving the Publick Peace of the ſaid Counties, and other parts of this Kingdom, in theſe diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Times, wherein no Lawful Government is eſtabliſhed in the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland. <hi>In witneſs whereof we have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſet our Hands this</hi> 18th <hi>Day of</hi> January, 1688.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Antrim, <hi>A. R. R. C. J. H.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>Down, <hi>J. H. J. H.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The forenamed Capt. <hi>Cole</hi> had Directions from my Lord <hi>Blanii,</hi> to prevail with us to Regiment our ſelves: So to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite in their Aſſociation, and to ſend One or Two of our Number to the Council of Five, then at <hi>Hilsborough,</hi> there to reſide, to receive ſuch Orders from time to time as the ſaid Council ſhould think moſt convenient, and to be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in our Undertakings accordingly. Upon which the Gentlemen of our County had ſeveral Meetings, but could not fix in any ſolid Method, nor jump in Opinion; ſo that Capt. <hi>Cole,</hi> returned to Lord <hi>Blanii</hi> with this following Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the <hi>Townſmen</hi> of <hi>Iniskilling.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOurs we have, for which we return humble and hearty Thanks. The Methods of your Proceedings we likewiſe received by Capt.</hi> Cole, <hi>a Meſſenger from Lord</hi> Blanii.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97788:14"/>
                     <hi>We have had ſeveral Meetings with the Gentlemen of this County, to joyn our ſelves in your Aſſociation; and now look upon our ſelves obliged to deal plainly with your Lordſhips: When firſt this poor Corporation unanimouſly joyned in a firm Reſolution of refuſing a Popiſh Gariſon, having a regard to the Conſequence of this Place, and the general preſervation of this Countrey; we addreſſed our ſelves to all the Gentlemen in it, to joyn with us, and ſtand by us, in this ſo neceſſary an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; but found the moſt Leading Men, not only to refuſe us, but to oppoſe our Reſolution to that degree, as to apprehend ſome of us, with intention to commit us to Gaol (if admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted). When this failed, they uſed their Intereſt and Power in hindering the Countrey to joyn toward our preſervation and their own, and endeavoured to repreſent us ill to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as we are credibly informed: Yet notwithſtanding theſe Diſcouragements,</hi> Guſtavus Hamilton, <hi>a Gentleman of our Countrey, took us by the Hand, and hitherto hath uſed his diligence and uttermoſt endeavours to ſupport us: He hath now Ten Companies of Foot in Arms, each conſiſting of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Two Private Men; a very good Troop of an Hundred Horſe, well armed with Carbines and Piſtols: And by an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument under our Hands, we have elected him Governour of this Place, and Colonel of our Forces.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Gentlemen that at firſt oppoſed our Intentions, have had of late ſeveral Meetings, and now ſhew a willingneſs to joyn, provided Sir</hi> Gerrard Ervin <hi>may be made Colonel of Horſe, and our Governour his Lieutenant Colonel, and Captain</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Colonel of Foot, ſo conſequently our Governour here, who is the Man of the world we moſt doubt, we having ſeveral Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhments from very good Hands, That our Fears are not groundleſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVe hope your Lordſhips conſidering our weak Riſe, the great Dangers we are now in, the extraordinary kindneſs and favour we have found from</hi> Guſtavus Hamilton, <hi>and the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97788:14"/>Reaſons we have to doubt the Sincerity of others, that your Lordſhips will be pleaſed to continue us in your favour, and believe that this is the true State of our Condition: we doubt not but evil inclined Spirits may ſet us forth otherwiſe, which we hope your Lordſhips will give no Credit to, but allow us the Liberty of ſubſcribing our ſelves,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhips faithful humble Servants, <hi>The Inhabitants of</hi> Iniskilling.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Immediately after this we iſſued this following Declaration.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE the Inhabitants of</hi> Iniskilling, <hi>with our Aſſociates, having regard to the great and eminent danger hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over our Heads; Receiving frequent Intelligence from all parts of this Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>That the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Papiſts are with all Diligence and Celerity arming themſelves (as is believed) to our deſtruction; and being, with the Aſſiſtance of Almighty God, reſolved to ſtand upon our Guards, we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto encouraged by a Declaration ſet forth by the Nobility and Gentry of the Counties of</hi> Antrim, Down <hi>and</hi> Ardmagh, <hi>ſatisfying us, That they have taken up Arms in their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, we therefore think fit, and do hereby admoniſh all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of this County, and the Countrey adjacent, to do the ſame: And for their future ſecurity and preſervation, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that all the Inhabitants of this County, and the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent parts, may aſſemble themſelves here with their Arms and Horſes, on</hi> Monday <hi>next, to joyn with us in this ſo neceſſary an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking; and there to be inliſted, to the end that Men may be appointed to Command them. VVe further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, That all the Neighbourhood may bring in their Proviſions to be ſecured for them in this Place, as a ſure Refuge for them to fly to in time of Trouble; And thoſe that do not now
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97788:15"/>lay up Proviſions for themſelves and families, ſhall not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to inhabit here, or relieved from hence hereafter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated at <hi>Iniskilling</hi> 
                        <date>the 27th <hi>of</hi> January, 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>A Copy of this, together with the following Letter, and a Copy of the Declaration of the Lords of the <hi>North-Eaſt,</hi> was ſent to all the Gentlemen in our Countrey.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE have here incloſed the Reſolutions of all the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the Counties of</hi> Down, Antrim <hi>and</hi> Ard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh, <hi>together with what we reſolve to do: This day we had by Expreſs, from an eminent Perſon in this Countrey, Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to be upon our Guard, and ready in Twelve Hours warning: Our earneſt Requeſt to you is, That you may give the ſame Inſtructions through your Countrey, and to appear here on</hi> Monday <hi>next, with what force you can raiſe, both Horſe and Foot, to the end they may be inliſted, and Officers appointed; where we will diſcover more to you, and conſult what further Meaſures may be taken for our preſervation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Emergency of Affairs. Your Diligence and Compliance in this is not doubted, by, SIR,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>
                           <hi>Jan.</hi> 27. 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your loving Friends, <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST AV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S HAMILTON, And the reſt of the Inhabitants of</hi> Iniskilling.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>According to our defire in the above-Letter, we had a General Rendezvous of our whole Countrey that joyned with us, where we had a very pretty Appearance: <hi>Gusta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus Hamilton,</hi> our Governour, continued Colonel, and Mr. <hi>Thomas Lloyd</hi> was made Lieutenant Colonel of our whole Forces. After this we enjoyed a conſiderable quiet,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97788:15"/>endeavouring to carry on our Fortifications, the moſt part of <hi>January</hi> and <hi>February,</hi> notwithſtanding the Winter. All this time we had frequent Correſpondence with my Lord of <hi>Kingſton,</hi> who had raiſed a very conſiderable Force, both of Horſe and Foot, in the Counties of <hi>Roſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and <hi>Sligo,</hi> and had made <hi>Sligo</hi> his Garriſon, which he endeavoured with all diligence to fortifie, with a firm Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of holding out that Place againſt all Oppoſition; but Ammunition being ſcarce with him, and receiving in <hi>February,</hi> Encouragement from Colonel <hi>Lundy,</hi> who at that time commanded all, to deſert <hi>Sligo,</hi> and march his Men to <hi>Derry,</hi> where he ſhould be accommodated with Proviſions for his Men, and forage for his Horſes: He left <hi>Sligo,</hi> and marched as far as <hi>Balliſhanon,</hi> towards <hi>Derry:</hi> He had no ſooner left his Garriſon, than the Enemy was in it; but he, brave Gentleman, met Aſſurance at <hi>Balliſhanon,</hi> that there was not any forage to be had at <hi>Derry</hi> for his Horſes; therefore conſtrained to continue where he was, quartering his Men along the Frontier, upon the <hi>North</hi> ſide of <hi>Lough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearne,</hi> while <hi>April</hi> following.</p>
            <p>In <hi>March</hi> we had intelligence, That King <hi>James</hi> was by the Convention of Eſtates in <hi>England,</hi> Voted to have Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, and had placed King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> in the Throne, who upon the 11th of <hi>March</hi> we Proclaimed, with all the Joy and Solemnity we could.</p>
            <p>Immediately, upon this, we received a Letter from Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Lundy,</hi> with one incloſed, from the Lords of the <hi>North-Eaſt.</hi> Colonel <hi>Lundy</hi>'s was in theſe Words:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE Incloſed is accompanied with ſeveral Letters, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating the March of the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Army Northward: To oppoſe which we are making all the Preparations poſſible, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho our Scarcity of Arms, Ammunition and Moneys, render
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97788:16"/>us not ſo fit as we ought for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking: But we will do what we can, and leave the Iſſue to Divine Providence, which orders all Events. On this occaſion it is likely that you and all our friends may be alarmed, if not formally attack'd by their Forces, were it but to keep you from affording us your help, or from giving them diverſion in their Attempts: wherefore you would do well to be strictly on your Guards, and if poſſible, (by Eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als) to open their Counſels and Deſigns; and what you know, pray communicate to your friends in this Countrey, and round about you, who, we hope, will obſerve the like Care, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a constant Correſpondence with all friends in theſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Times. I am reſolved to march hence within a day or two, with what force I can raiſe in this Countrey, to</hi> Donganan, <hi>and deſire you to have all Men ready to march that were deſigned for it, that as ſoon as I write for them, they may come immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to the place aſſigned for our Rendezvous. I remain,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>For Sir <hi>John Hume,</hi> and the reſt of the Gentlemen of the County of <hi>Farma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagh,</hi> Theſe.</dateline>
                     <signed>Gentlemen, Your faithful Servant, <hi>ROBERT L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDY.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The incloſed from the Lord <hi>Mountalexander,</hi> and other Gentlemen of the <hi>North-Eaſt</hi> to Colonel <hi>Lundy.</hi> Dated at <hi>Lough-brickland, March</hi> the 9th, 1688. was as followeth:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SInce our laſt to you, dated the</hi> 6th, <hi>we have this day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the incloſed; and Mr.</hi> Osburne <hi>was here himſelf, and confirms the Contents, with ſeveral Circumstances, which perſwades us of the Truth of it: And therefore we moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly intreat you to march up towards</hi> Nury, <hi>with all poſſible diligence, with what Men you can, with as much Proviſions
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97788:16"/>and Neceſſaries as can be carried; and let us know by Expreſs of their March, and their Numbers. We remain,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Sir, You are deſired to give notice to all Friends.</dateline>
                        <dateline>To the Honourable Col. <hi>Lundy,</hi> in <hi>Derry.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your Humble Servants,
<list>
                              <item>Mountalexander.</item>
                              <item>James Hamilton.</item>
                              <item>William Cunningham.</item>
                              <item>Richard Johnſton.</item>
                              <item>Mar. Midleton.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Mr. <hi>Osburn</hi>'s Letter to Lord <hi>Mountalexander.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ON the</hi> 6th <hi>instant, I was introduced by my Lord</hi> Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, <hi>to my Lord Deputy's Preſence, in the Castle of</hi> Dublin: <hi>I have his Paſs to come and go through and back from</hi> Ulſter. <hi>And tho I have not his Excellencies expreſs Commiſſion, yet I aſſure you, I am at leaſt permitted by the Lord Deputy, to acquaint the Chief, and others of the</hi> Ulſter-<hi>Aſſociation, with his diſcourſe to me; which was to the effect following: Viz.</hi> That his Excellency doth not delight in the Blood of the Proteſtants of the ſaid Province; but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, highly reſents their taking and continuing in Arms; the Affront done by them to Him, and His Majeſties Government thereby; and by ſome Indignities done to the late Proclamation of Clemency, iſſued and dated</p>
                     <p>Notwithſtanding whereof, is willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſaid Province into Protection; Provided, they immediately deliver to his Army, to His Majeſties Uſe, their Arms, and ſerviceable Horſes; and provided they deliver to his Excellency theſe Three Perſons; <hi>Viz.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> if they ſtay in the Kingdom, and they may be had. And for further mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of his Deſign to prevent Blood, is willing to grant
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97788:17"/>Safe Conduct, even to the ſaid Three Perſons, or any of their Party, from his Excellency, and to and from Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Commander of a part of his Army, if they intend any Peaceable and Reaſonable Treaty: But withal, will not, upon the ſaid Account, or any other, ſtop the March of that part of his ſaid Army, no, not for an Hour: And if it ſhall appear in ſuch Treaty, that they took up Arms meerly for Self-preſervation, he will pardon even the ſaid Three Perſons: But is hopeleſs that any ſuch thing can be made appear, being many of them have accepted and received Commiſſions from the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and diſplayed his Colours in the Field, as he is credibly inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If theſe Terms be not immediately agreed to, he will, with a part of his Army, fight them; which part he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends ſhall be at <hi>Nury</hi> on <hi>Monday</hi> the 11th of this Inſtant, which will from thence march to <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Colraine</hi> and <hi>Londonderry,</hi> as his Excellency intends: And that the Countrey <hi>Iriſh,</hi> not of the Army, Man, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and Boy, now all Armed with Half Pikes and Baggo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, in the Counties of <hi>Cavan, Managhan, Tyrone</hi> and <hi>Londonderry,</hi> &amp;c. will, on the Approach of the ſaid part of the Army, and Reſiſtance thereunto made, immediately en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> of the ſaid Counties; which Force and Violence of the Rabble, his Excellency ſays, he cannot reſtrain. <hi>Theſe are the Heads of what I can offer to you from his Excellency's own Mouth: But I intend to be at</hi> Hilsborough <hi>to Night.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Alex. Osburne.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Two, as I ſaid before, came incloſed in Col. <hi>Lun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi>'s, directed to Sir <hi>John Hame,</hi> Bar. to be communicated to the reſt of the Gentlemen in the County of <hi>Farmanagh. Haſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, you may believe, put us upon our more ſtrict Guard;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97788:17"/>but Col. <hi>Lundy,</hi> in place of moving, as he mentions in his Letter, ordered the Garriſon then kept at <hi>Donganan,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert that place, and march down to the <hi>Lagau:</hi> Upon which all the <hi>Britiſh</hi> in that Country fled to <hi>Strabane,</hi> the <hi>Lagau,</hi> and <hi>Derry.</hi> He likewiſe wrote Letters to us (as he did to the County of <hi>Cavan</hi> Gentlemen that were then in Arms), im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to bring off the Women and Children, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to the <hi>Lagau:</hi> But we had fixed our Reſolution other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, being highly ſenſible, that holding out that Place of <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> was the only Let to hinder the <hi>Conaught</hi> Forces joyning with thoſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lster;</hi> and conſequently all the Support that <hi>Derry</hi> could expect: For had we deſerted that Place, all <hi>Ireland</hi> then was in the Papiſts Hands, ſave <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donderry,</hi> which of it ſelf could not poſſibly ſubſiſt, or be able to hold out againſt the whole Power of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Whereas, on the other Hand, our keeping that Place would, at leaſt, (if we could not aſſiſt to relieve <hi>Derry</hi>) be a great means of diverting their Force from uniting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen of the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi> about the 20th of <hi>March,</hi> the Weather being very ſtormy, and the Ways extreme deep, ſcarce-paſſable, all, in a moſt diſtracted and confuſed manner, deſerted their Countrey, and fled to <hi>Inis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing;</hi> telling us, that they had received poſitive Orders from Col. <hi>Lundy</hi> ſo to do, leaving the moſt part of what they had behind them; And the poor People, in a moſt ſtarving and deplorable condition, throng'd into our Town, filling all Corners full, ſo that there was above 200 Families forced to get into the Church, the Seſſions-houſe and School-houſe being likewiſe filled. Their Officers uſed their utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavours to perſwade our Governour to do the like; <hi>Viz.</hi> to deſert <hi>Iniskilling;</hi> and indeed ſome that we expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed better things from, were likewiſe of Opinion, that it was our ſafeſt way: Which, had this Advice been followed, it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97788:18"/>would certainly have ruined the whole Proteſtant Intereſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and given the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army the opportunity of paſſing into <hi>Scotland</hi> or <hi>England</hi> at their pleaſure; but Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>John Rider</hi> gave ſo weighty and forcible Reaſons of the Neceſſity of holding that Place, that he over-ruled all, and confirmed ſeveral (that were really wavering) to be firm in our former Reſolution: But when we had fully pryed into the Reaſons of the County of <hi>Cavan</hi> Gentry ſo deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Country, being a good Party of Men, and having ſeveral Strengths that they might have held out, we found, that it was more out of fear of a Party under the Command of the Lord <hi>Galmoy,</hi> that had marched into their Country, than any thing elſe that had brought them off, altho I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they had a Letter from Col. <hi>Lundy</hi> to that purpoſe. The Lord <hi>Galmoy</hi> indeed, with the beſt part of his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Horſe, ſome Dragoons, with the Rabble of the Countrey, came as far as <hi>Belturbet,</hi> ſurpriſing by the way Dean <hi>Dixey</hi>'s Houſe, taking his Eldeſt Son, who was Capt. of a Troop of Horſe, and one <hi>Edward Charleton,</hi> his Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, Priſoners.</p>
            <p>The County of <hi>Cavan</hi> Men ſtayed Three Days at <hi>Inis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing,</hi> in which time Lord <hi>Galmoy</hi> marched his Men as far as <hi>Liſnaskey,</hi> a pretty Village within Ten Miles of us, where there is a tolerable ſtrong Caſtle belonging to <hi>Charles Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>. The Night e'er he came there, he ſent a Summons to <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> commanding them to deliver up the Place, their Arms and ſerviceable Horſes to him, for the King's uſe, who, as he ſaid, was then in <hi>Dublin;</hi> and to receive Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: Which if we refuſed, he was come with an Army to reduce that Country to the King's Obedience, which he would do by Force: And if we now denied to receive theſe Conditions, we ſhould not be favoured with the like here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Upon Receipt of this Summons, the Governour called all the Officers belonging to the Town together, who with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97788:18"/>a unanimous Voice, reſolved to defend the Place to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and return'd an Anſwer immediately to the Lord <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moy,</hi> That they owned no Power ſave Their Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> that they had lately Proclaimed, and that for their uſe they would hold out the Town to the laſt Man.</p>
            <p>Then we prepared, as indeed it was ever our intention, to meet <hi>Galmoy,</hi> and fight him e'er he came near our Town, deſiring the County of <hi>Cavan</hi> men to joyn with us in giving him a Bruſh; then, if they had a mind, they might march on to <hi>Derry;</hi> but they abſolutely refuſed it, getting out of Town with all ſpeed imaginable. We then made, by the Governour's Orders, Proclamation, <hi>That all thoſe who left the County of</hi> Cavan, <hi>and were now upon their march to</hi> Derry, <hi>ſhould take their Wives and Children along with them; elſe any that were left, ſhould be turned out of Town.</hi> This occaſioned the ſtay of Three or Four Companies of Foot, moſt of them having Wives and Children, and not able to get them off; but all the reſt, both Horſe and Foot, went off, with ſome of the Officers of theſe Companies that ſtayed.</p>
            <p>Our Governour then drew out what Force we had, with a reſolution to meet Lord <hi>Galmoy,</hi> and fight him; upon the intelligence of which he retreated to <hi>Crum,</hi> a Caſtle holding out for us, lying upon the <hi>Eaſt</hi> ſide of <hi>Loughearne,</hi> Three Miles below <hi>Belturbet,</hi> which he beſieged, drawing on Two Peices of Battering Cannon, as was ſuppoſed, with great Noiſe, and imaginary Difficulty; which coming to our knowledge there was a Detachment of about 200 Fire-locks immediately ordered by the Governour, for the re-inforcing <hi>Crum</hi>-Garriſon, while the other Forces could be in readineſs to march to their Relief. Theſe were ſent, ſome by Land, ſome by Water, marching by Night; but Day appearing e'er they got the length of the <hi>Castle,</hi> the Enemy uſed all their endeavour to hinder our Mens landing, firing ſmall ſhot ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97788:19"/>thick upon them, but killed none, ſave one Boteman: Our Men likewiſe, together with thoſe in the <hi>Castle,</hi> fired thick upon the Enemy, killing ſeveral of them, and by force got into the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> who when they were joyned, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſallied out, beat the Enemy off from their Trenches, killing 30 or 40 of them, and took their Two great Guns, which proved to be Boxes of Tin about Two Foot and an half long, Five Inches <hi>Diameter,</hi> well bound about with pitched Canvaſs, and ſmall Cording. They had fired one of them with a Wooden Bullet, and burſt out her Britch: Our Men got ſome Arms, two Suits of Armor, and ſeveral other things of value. Lord <hi>Galmoy</hi> upon this retreated to <hi>Belturbet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>E're <hi>Galmoy</hi> came the length of <hi>Liſnaskey,</hi> a curſed fellow, one <hi>Kemp,</hi> with ſome of the Rabble of the Country, his Conſorts, burnt that pretty Village, to the great loſs of the Inhabitants, and the worthy Gentleman that owned it, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a prejudice to <hi>In is killing,</hi> it being capable of quartering above a Regiment of Men, and of being made a Frontier to us, we being much ſtraitned in <hi>In is killing</hi> for Lodgings. But e're the Town was burnt, we had brought from thence a many Tuns of Iron, belonging to Mr. <hi>Belfore,</hi> and moſt of the Lead of his Houſe, which proved very ſerviceable to us, both to Horſe and Foot.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Galmoy</hi> having retreated to <hi>Belturbet,</hi> ſends to Lieut. Col. <hi>Creighton,</hi> Commander at <hi>Crum</hi> (whoſe Houſe it is), he having one <hi>Bryan Mac Guier,</hi> a Captain amongſt the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> Priſoner; and intreats that <hi>Mac Guier</hi> might be ſent him, obliging himſelf upon his Honour to ſend Capt. <hi>Dixey</hi> in exchange for <hi>Mac Guier.</hi> Lieut. Col. <hi>Creighton,</hi> upon this, ſends <hi>Mac Guier</hi> to <hi>Belturbet;</hi> but the honeſt Lord in place of making good his obliged Honour, called a Court Marſhal, where he had both <hi>Dixey</hi> and <hi>Charlton</hi> tried, and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for levying Men by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Commiſſion, which was found in their Pockets. They, as it is ſaid, were
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97788:19"/>offered their Lives, if they would turn <hi>Papiſts;</hi> (which if they had done, I preſume they would have been ſerved as formerly theſe ſort of people uſed to ſerve <hi>Protestants,</hi> who at any time, through the fear of Death, would turn <hi>Papiſts</hi> for the preſervation of their Lives, which was <hi>to hang them when in a good Mind,</hi> as they call'd it): But they (altho young men) refuſing ſo to do, were both hanged upon Mr. <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Sign-poſt, and after, their Heads cut off, and kickt about the Streets for Foot-balls.</p>
            <p>About this time we ſent again a Party of Horſe to <hi>Derry,</hi> for a ſupply of Arms and Ammunition, having intelligence that good ſtore was arrived there from <hi>England;</hi> but all we could procure from Col. <hi>Lundy,</hi> he having the ſole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of that Place was, Threeſcore old Muſquets, moſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Stocks or Locks, and Five ſmall Barrels of Gunpowder, which came ſafe to <hi>Iniskilling.</hi> We ſoon fixed up the Arms.</p>
            <p>Now was the Army under the Command of Lieut. Gen. <hi>Hamilton,</hi> upon their march to the <hi>North-East,</hi> where they met but with ſmall reſiſtance, Sir <hi>Arthur Reiden</hi> being the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, as we were informed, that endeavoured to give them oppoſition at <hi>Drummore,</hi> from whence he was conſtrained (having but a ſmall Party with him) to retreat to <hi>Hilsborough;</hi> but coming there, and finding that the Lord <hi>Mountalexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> with thoſe under him, had deſerted that place, and fled to <hi>Donoghadee,</hi> the ready Port for <hi>Scotland,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> made the beſt of his way to <hi>Antrim,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Colraine,</hi> where Lieut. Gen. <hi>Hamilton</hi> followed, meeting with no reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance while he was there, oppoſed by Major <hi>Guſtavus Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton,</hi> who beat him back, and forced him to retreat to <hi>Ballimony;</hi> but he after, with his whole Army, paſt the <hi>Bandwater,</hi> at a place called <hi>Portglanone,</hi> ſo got into the County of <hi>Londonderry;</hi> upon which Alarm, Col. <hi>Lundy,</hi> and the other Officers at <hi>Derry,</hi> held a Counſel of War; the Reſult of which was as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:97788:20"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Londonderry, April the 13th, 1689.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AT a General Counſel of War, reſolved unanimouſly, That on</hi> Monday <hi>next, by Ten of the Clock in the Morning, all Officers and Soldiers, Horſe, Dragoons, and Foot, and all other Armed Men whatſoever, of our Forces and Friends inliſted, and not inlisted, that can, and will fight for their Country and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion against</hi> Popery, <hi>ſhall appear in the fittest Ground near</hi> Clady-Ford, Lifford, <hi>and</hi> Long Caſſiway, <hi>as ſhall be to their ſeveral reſpective quarters, there to draw up in Battalions, to be ready to fight the</hi> Enemy, <hi>to preſerve our Lives, and all that is dear to us, from them; and all Officers and Soldiers of Horſe, Foot, and Dragoons, and others that are Armed, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be then there, in order to the purpoſe aforeſaid, and to bring a Weeks Proviſion at least with them for Men, and as much Forage as they can for Horſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>Fra. Hamilton.</item>
                           <item>Kil. Braſier.</item>
                           <item>Jo. Richardſon.</item>
                           <item>Will. Hamilton.</item>
                           <item>J. Barry.</item>
                           <item>Will. Stewart.</item>
                           <item>Nic. Atkinſon.</item>
                           <item>Robert Lundy.</item>
                           <item>Blany.</item>
                           <item>James Hamilton.</item>
                           <item>Hugh Montgomery.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This was ſent us to <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> accompanied with a very preſſing Letter, acquainting us of the Enemies paſſing the <hi>Band,</hi> urging the neceſſity of our leaving that Place, it not being tenable; and the inavoidable danger we were in, if the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army prevail'd at <hi>Clady,</hi> where, he ſaid, he reſolved to fight them.</p>
            <p>The like was ſent to my Lord <hi>Kingſton,</hi> who lay 20 miles below us, ſince his being brought off from <hi>Sligo,</hi> with this following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOu ſee the Reſult of our Counſel of War, and we hope your Lordſhip will give us your help and aſſiſtance. In haſte, I am, Your Lordſhip's most Humble Servant,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>April. 1689.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Robert Lundy.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97788:20"/>
            <p>We at <hi>In is killing</hi> reſolved not to ſtir; but my Lord <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston</hi> receiving <hi>Lundy</hi>'s Letter about. Twelve of the Clock upon <hi>Sunday</hi> at Night, at <hi>Balliſhanan,</hi> where his Lordſhip then lay, his men lying quartered abroad in the Country, marched with a few Horſe, as early as he could, next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards <hi>Clady,</hi> leaving Orders for the reſt of his Horſe and Foot to follow him: But e'er he got that length, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy had paſt the <hi>Clady-water,</hi> put all <hi>Lundy</hi>'s Party to the rout, and were upon the purſuit; ſo that my L. could not joyn them, to make any oppoſition; therefore counter-marched. And now <hi>Lundy</hi> beginning to be ſuſpected by moſt men, and believing by his Treachery, that all would be loſt, many Gentlemen; nay, people of all ſorts, endeavoured to get out of the Kingdom: my Lord of <hi>Kingſton</hi> left the Kingdom likewiſe, but ſent to <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Two Troops of Horſe, and Six Companies of Foot, all brave men. This was a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Addition to our Strength. Now we reſolved firmly, as we ever had done before, to ſtick by that place whilſt a man of us were alive. When <hi>Lundy</hi> ſent his laſt Letter to us, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat us off from <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> there was one ſent from an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Hand, directed to Lieut. <hi>Carmick,</hi> which was this:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WE know that there are ſome Expreſſes gone from hence laſt night and this day, that gives an account of the ill ſucceſs that attends our Forces; and that it is to be feared it will be hard for any to eſcape from</hi> Colraine <hi>hither; it is likewiſe belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by most, that advice is ſent to</hi> Iniskilling <hi>to deſert that place, and retire to</hi> Derry, <hi>which will tend to the ruin of all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Intereſt in</hi> Ulſter, <hi>and, for ought we know, in the whole Kingdom. There are many well wiſhers to your Town and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, that believe it were better to ſtay there than retire. It is a nice point to adviſe a friend in: what is to be done, muſt be with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, either to come away immediately, or reſolve to defend that place. Take ſpeedy counſel, and God of his infinite mercy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you, that you may eſcape the cruelty of your Enemies. This place will be ſo thronged, that the Walls will not contain the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Sir,</hi> I am yours.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97788:21"/>
            <p>We were fixed in our reſolutions e're this came, and indeed had ſome doubts of <hi>Lundy</hi>'s Sincerity: Whether he deſerved it, or not, I can't ſay, yet his uſage to my L. <hi>Kingſton</hi> was ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious-like; for after bringing him off from <hi>Sligo,</hi> as I ſaid before, promiſing him Proviſions both for Horſe and Men, and then receiving Orders for his ſtaying at <hi>Balliſhanan,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging he had no Forrage for his Horſe, the Enemy having poſſeſſed themſelves of <hi>Sligo</hi> as ſoon as my Lord left it, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated our firſt Jealouſie: but to palliate his ſo doing, e're Lieut. Gen. <hi>Hamilton</hi> paſt the <hi>Band,</hi> he wrote this following Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to my Lord.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YEſterday I received a Letter from the Earl of</hi> Shrewsbury, <hi>by his Majesties Command, giving encouragement of ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Aid from</hi> England, <hi>and expreſſing his Majeſties great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for us, and the Zeal of both Houſes, and full compliance with his Majeſties gracious intentions, I have formed a Garriſon here, and will provide your Lordſhip and Capt.</hi> Coote <hi>accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation for</hi> 80 <hi>Horſe, if you pleaſe to come over hither, where it's likely there will be occaſion very ſoon, if you come and bring Garrons with you. You would do well to cauſe your men to load, and bring hither as much Sheaf-Oats, and as much other forrage as you can, which ſhall be preſerved for your own men. I am in haste, My Lord,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Londonderry,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>April</hi> 11, 1689.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt affectionate humble Servant, <hi>Rob. Lundy.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>You may ſee by this how <hi>Lundy</hi> dealt by that brave and Honourable Perſon, firſt promiſing him Forrage for all his Horſes, and Proviſions for his men, while he perſwaded him off from <hi>Sligo;</hi> then but for 80 Horſe; Whereas my Lord had at leaſt Ten full Troops, Two of Dragoons included. This occaſioned my Lord's ſtay at <hi>Balliſhanan;</hi> for unleſs he brought Forrage with him, as you may ſee by the above-Letter, he could expect none, when all <hi>Lundy</hi>'s Promiſes ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in this, to ſecure what Forrage my Lord ſhould bring with him, for his own Men.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:97788:21"/>
            <p>About the middle of <hi>April</hi> we of <hi>Iniskilling</hi> having intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence brought us, that the Enemy were about ſettling a Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon in <hi>Trillick,</hi> a place nine miles wide of us, upon the ſtode to <hi>Derry,</hi> we did believe they would be but unneighbourly Gueſts, therefore thought it convenient to prevent their ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling there, and to that purpoſe, being well reinforced by my Lord <hi>Kingſtones</hi> men, we marched in the night under the Command of Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> (under whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct we never failed accompliſhing what we deſigned, but without him, could not, or never did any thing) and came to <hi>Trillick</hi> very early in the morning, where we diſcovered a Party marching towards us, our Horſe advanced with what ſpeed they could; and our Lieut. Col. alighting, led the Foot through the Bogs and Mountains, the neareſt way he could; with a reſolution to have attack'd the Enemy, but they diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering us retreated, leaving all their Cattle and Baggage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them: The Lieutenant Colonel perceiving this, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately detached an hundred Fire-locks, commanding Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>Mac Carmick</hi> to lead them on with all ſpeed, to try if poſſible he could force the Enemy to a ſtand, while the Body could get up; the Country being ſo bogy that there was no marching for Horſe, but by the Roads; but after near ſix hours hard purſuit, we were conſtrained to make an halt, the Enemy diſperſing, and every man ſhifting the beſt way he could for himſelf, we preyed all the Country, and ſo return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a conſiderable Booty, which was divided amongſt the private men.</p>
            <p>We thought it now time, the more to prevent both the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencies of the private Souldiers, and to take away all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions in the future, that any man might have for declining our intereſt, to bind ourſelves by Oath, the one to the other, and to this purpoſe, at a general Randevous, we were all ſworn as followeth,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97788:22"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Oath adminiſtred to the Governour.</head>
                     <p>I Guſtavus Hamilton <hi>do ſwear by God, and the Holy Contents of this Book, That I ſhall Truely, Sincerely, and Faithfully execute and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Office and Place of Governour of</hi> Iniskilling, <hi>according to my utmoſt Power and Ability, and that I ſhall with my Life and Fortune de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt, together with the Inhabitants of this Town, and all others under my Command, and that I ſhall not act nor do any thing contrary to the Conſent and General Advice of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers under my Command, but ſhall from time to time and at all times ſtand by and ſupport the ſaid Intereſt; neither diſſert it, nor this Place without being by Force beaten from thence.</hi> So help me God.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Oath of the Officers.</head>
                     <p>I A. B. <hi>do hereby testifie and declare, and upon the Holy Evangelists ſwear, That I will own and acknowledge</hi> Guſtavus Hamilton, <hi>
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Chief Governour of this Town of</hi> Iniskilling; <hi>and ſhall give due obedience to him in all his lawful Commands; and ſhall to the uttermoſt of my Power and Ability protect and defend him and this Place, with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try adjacent, together with the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt with my Life and Fortune, against all that ſhall endeavour to ſubvert the ſame; and that I ſhall be Juſt and Faithful, in giving my Sincere Opinion and Advice, in all Counſels whereunto I am called, for the General Good and Preſervation of the Intereſt aforeſaid.</hi> So help me God.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Oath of the Private Souldiers.</head>
                     <p>I D. H. <hi>do hereby Teſtifie and Declare, and upon the Holy Evangeliſts Swear, That I will Own and Acknowledge</hi> Guſtavus Hamilton, <hi>
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Chief Governour of this Town of</hi> Inniskilling; <hi>and ſhall give due Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him and my Superiour Officers in all his and their Commands and ſhall to the uttermost of my Power and Ability, defend him, them, and this Place, with the Country adjacent, together with the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion and Intereſt, with my Life and Fortune, againſt All that ſhall endeavour to ſubvert the ſame.</hi> So help me God, and the Holy Contents of this Book.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:97788:22"/>
            <p>Theſe Oaths were Adminiſtred to every Individual perſon according to their reſpective poſts; and upon the 28th, of <hi>April,</hi> we hearing that there was a Garriſon of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> put into the Caſtle of <hi>Ougher,</hi> a very conſiderable ſtrength, with a good Baunwale and Flankers, lying upon the Road to <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont,</hi> eighteen miles from us; we again were drawn out under the Conduct of Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Loyde,</hi> and in one night marched to <hi>Ougher,</hi> coming in early upon <hi>Sunday</hi> morning, yet notwithſtanding our private and ſpeedy march, the Enemy had notice of our approach, and diſſerted their Garriſon taking away with them what they could carry; we (ſeizing what Cattle they had, not being able to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them) Preyed their Country, Burnt their Caſtle, Levelled their Fortifications, and ſo left <hi>Ougher;</hi> Taking our way through the Mountains, to a place called <hi>Shannake,</hi> another ſtrong Houſe they kept Garriſon in, neer to <hi>Clowniſh,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to <hi>Daniel Eccles,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> the Gentleman that firſt gave us notice of the two Companies approach to <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> whoſe Houſe we had a great deſire to ſave, and place a Garriſon there of our own men; upon <hi>Munday</hi> at night we came within a mile and a half of it (being toyled with our long march, and the bogineſs of the Mountains) we reſted three or four hours, with a reſolution of falling in upon the Enemies Garriſon by break of day, but they having notice of our approach, by ſome of the Country <hi>Iriſh</hi> flying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; e're we could poſſibly fall in with them, fled and ſet the Houſe on Fire, burning to the ground both it and all the Office houſes belonging to it; we purſued them hard into the County of <hi>Managhan,</hi> but could not over take them; we Preyed all the Country about, fetching off both from the County of <hi>Managhan</hi> and part of the County of <hi>Canau,</hi> a great deal of black Cattle, many Horſes, which we loaded with the growth of the Country, as Meal, Malt, Wheat, Oats, Butter, Bedcloaths, and the like, a conſiderable number of Sheep, and ſo return'd to <hi>Iniskilling</hi> the ſecond day of <hi>May;</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:97788:23"/>Black Cattle was not at all deer with us, nor any other ſort of Proviſion during the whole time of our Troubles; but this made them much cheaper than formerly: For now we could have bought a good milk Cow for ſixteen or eighteen Pence, and a dry one for ſix pence.</p>
            <p>We had reſted but one day, when there came an Expreſs from Captain <hi>Falliat</hi> Commander of <hi>Balliſhanan,</hi> a Town with a ſtrong Caſtle twenty miles below us, ſtanding likewiſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſide of <hi>Loughcarne</hi> near the Sea; that there was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Party of Horſe and Foot from <hi>Conaught,</hi> ſat down before it; the Enemy had Summoned them to deliver the Town and Caſtle, which Summons he ſent to us, deſiring ſpeedy relief; Lieutenant Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi> marched next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a conſiderable Party both of Horſe and Foot to raiſe the Seige: The Enemy hearing of our approach drew off the greateſt part of their Strength, both Horſe and Foot to a place called <hi>Bellick,</hi> three miles nearer us, and there poſted themſelves very advantagioufly, there being but one narrow Paſs by which they could be attacked, a Bog running from the ſide of <hi>Loughearne</hi> all the way to <hi>Bandruſe,</hi> ſeven miles to the left hand, not known to be paſſable in any place ſave where the Road led through it, cloſe to the Lough ſide; this the Enemy had ſtrongly barrocaded, and before their Works had broke down a Bridg, and ſo raiſed the way that it could not be paſſed, Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi> eſpying this, cauſed Faggots to be cut immediately for making the Bog paſſable, and ſo drew up againſt the Enemy, they making great Huzza's, and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us to come on and fight them; our Stomacks were as good as theirs, if not better for that Trade, and as we were advancing to force our way, God Almighty ſent a man, from whence I know not, that offered to lead us ſafe through the Bog, towards our left Hand, and that our Horſe ſhould not need to alight, nor to uſe their Faggots; he was as good as his word: when we had paſt the Bog our advance Guard, led by Capt. <hi>Atchiſon,</hi> indeavoured to get, if poſſible, the Right
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97788:23"/>Flank of the Enemy, ſo to prevent their eſcaping to the Mountains; but they eſpying it, and our Body coming on, began to move orderly towards their Right, as if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to prevent their being flanked, we obſerving their motion marched extream hard, but e're we could come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhot the Enemies Foot broke, and run clear away to the Mountains: The Horſe which were upon the Left of the Foot, betwixt them and the Lough, ſtood while our Horſe were ready to charge them, then wheeled to the left, and ſo ran for it without firing a ſhot; our Horſe perſued ſeven miles, and had not the Night come on I preſume few of them had eſcaped: There was none that fought ſave one <hi>Fitzgerald,</hi> who being overtaken upon his flight, by one Lieutenant <hi>Moloye</hi> of our Party, fired his three ſhot briskly upon him, and had certainly killed him had he wanted his Armour; but when his ſhot was ſpent they fought it with their Swords, while ſome of our men came up and took <hi>Fitzgerald</hi> Priſoner; he was very much wounded, but becauſe of his courage was carefully looked after, and brought to <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered: There were killed in the perſute and hundred and ninety Horſe. Our foot marched unto <hi>Balliſhanon,</hi> where they took about ſixty Priſoners in the <hi>Fiſh Iſland</hi> and about it, knocking ſome others on the head that were left to continue the Siege, they not knowing that their Army was broke, while our men came upon them; we had the Plunder of their Camp, which was but beggarly; got ſeveral good ſerviceable Horſes, two ſmall Canon, ſome good Arms, and a ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Amunition; and having fully done what we went about, returned to <hi>Iniskilling;</hi> this was the firſt Ingagement (if it may be ſo called) that we had with the Enemy, where we loſt not one man, nor any wounded ſave Cornet King, that had a ſhot in the Face receiving a Carabine from one of the Iriſh Horſe after giving him quarters, but the Horſe-man was immediately killed by one <hi>James King,</hi> a friend of the Cornets, who ſoon recovered of his Wound.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:97788:24"/>
            <p>During the time of our <hi>Ougher</hi> and <hi>Clowniſh</hi> Expedition, the Governour began a Fort upon a Hill at the Eaſt end of our Town, a very regular Fortification, laid out by Major <hi>Hart</hi> and Major <hi>Rider,</hi> both good Mathematicians; which was carried on very effectually by the diligence of Major <hi>Rider,</hi> who ſpared no Pains while he finiſhed his Work <hi>June</hi> following, with a Line of Communication from it to the Eaſt-Bridg, it commands the whole Town, and clears the Roads leading to it on that end.</p>
            <p>Soon after our Return from <hi>Balliſhannon,</hi> we had Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that the Iriſh were endeavouring to get to a head in the County of <hi>Canau,</hi> keeping a Gariſon at <hi>Redhill,</hi> a ſtrong and large Houſe belonging to <hi>Francis White,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother at a place called <hi>Ballinacarig,</hi> to remove which, we again marched under the Command of Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyde,</hi> where upon the Road <hi>Crum</hi> Gariſon joyned us, we were twenty two pair of Colours, and a ſtrong Party of Horſe: when we had marched up to <hi>Wattle-bridg</hi> near the Borders of the County of <hi>Canau,</hi> we eſpied the Enemy on the other ſide, and did expect they would have diſputed that Paſs, the Bridg being down, and the Water deep; but upon our Approach, ſeeing us reſolved to force our way, they withdrew to the next Hill, ſo we paſt the Ford without Oppoſition, and marched up towards them again; but they ſtill retreated from place to place, while they came to <hi>Redhill</hi> Houſe, where they left part of their Number to defend it, the reſt going off to <hi>Ballinacarig,</hi> we immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately drew up againſt <hi>Redhill</hi> Houſe, altho late in the Evening, and upon Summons, they ſurrendred upon mercy; there was not any thing taken from the Priſoners ſave their Arms; neither did we prejudice the Houſe out of tenderneſs to the Gentleman that owned it, he himſelf being in <hi>England,</hi> and his Brother commanding a Company of Foot in our Party at that time.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:97788:24"/>
            <p>Next Morning early we marched to <hi>Ballinacarig</hi> Caſtle a very ſtrong Houſe well valted, that had held out a long time in the former War of <hi>Ireland,</hi> what Priſoners were took at <hi>Red hill,</hi> we had along with us, we drew up againſt it about four a Clock in the Aftenoon, and upon Summons, the Garriſon ſurrendered, upon Condition of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, with what Priſoners were taken at <hi>Red-hill,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Women and Children at Liberty, with only their wearing Cloaths along with them, which was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and they Convoyed ſafe off; leaving the Caſtle, their Arms and Ammunition, with abundance of Proviſions, Houſhold goods, and much Rich plunder; when we had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved all was in it, we undermined the Houſe, ſet it on fire, and levelled it with the ground; it lying a great way from <hi>Iniskilling</hi> in the Enemies Country; therefore not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for us to keep a Garriſon at ſuch diſtance.</p>
            <p>In this Expedition we ſcoured the Country near as far as <hi>Kells</hi> and <hi>Finnah,</hi> where we drove off betwixt five and ſix Thouſand black Cattle, a many Sheep, and five Hundred and odd Horſes, moſt of which we loaded with Meal, Wheat and Malt, ſo returned to <hi>Iniskilling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after we had intelligence, that our approach ſo near <hi>Dublin</hi> (for we were within Twenty ſeven miles of it) had put that place in a great conſternation, imagining we would have marched that length, our Number conſiſting in their opinion of Fourteen or Fifteen Thouſand men, and indeed if the Proteſtants there, had received any aſſurance of our coming, ſo to have been in a readineſs to have joyned us; I do not know but we might have gone a great length in taking that City, there being but few of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> there at that time; yet our Number being ſmall, and wanting Arms and Ammunition, we thought it more adviſeable, to return then run ſo deſperate a Riske.</p>
            <p>Collonel <hi>Sarsfield</hi> at this time lay incamped at a place called <hi>Manor Hamilton,</hi> in a ſtone Deer Park of Sir <hi>William Gors,</hi> with ſome ſix or ſeven Thouſand men; upon the Weſt ſide
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97788:25"/>of us, at ſixteen or ſeventeen miles diſtance; he ſent a Drum with Propoſals of Exchange of Priſoners, which our Governor embraced, expecting to have had Sir <hi>Thomas Suthwell,</hi> and thoſe taken with him enlarged; to that purpoſe he ſends a Liſt of the Priſoners taken at <hi>Balliſhanan,</hi> intimating his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to <hi>Sarsfield,</hi> but he excuſed himſelf, alledging that Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was to be taken into <hi>England,</hi> to be exchanged for ſome there; and having no Priſoners with him of ours, he ſeiſes all the protected Proteſtants, that lived near <hi>Slygo,</hi> clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into Goal, urging them to Petition our Governour for their enlargement; which the Governour at firſt refuſed to do; they not being taken as Priſoners of War, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of their own private dwellings, to be made ſerviſable in redeeming theſe that we had taken in actual Armes; but ſome of their Wives having liberty to come to us, but in a ſad enough Condition, intreating every day for the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Husbands out of miſery; our Governor at laſt conſented; and the exchange agreed upon: Captain <hi>Francis Gore,</hi> with a party of <hi>Firelockes,</hi> Gonvoyed the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Eight miles, where he met a party of <hi>Sarsfields</hi> men, with the poor Proteſtants; whom he brought back with him, and one Captain <hi>Jackſon</hi> being amongſt them; upon his coming to <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> had liberty to inliſt the others that were brought off with him, of whom he made up a good Company, who were Armed immediately.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of <hi>June,</hi> there were two Troops of Horſe, <hi>viz;</hi> Captain <hi>Francis Gores,</hi> and Captain <hi>Arnold Casbies</hi> ſent to Garriſon at <hi>Trillick,</hi> a Houſe nine miles off us, upon the Road to <hi>Omagh,</hi> where they had intelligence of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Dragoon horſes belonging to the Garriſon of <hi>Omagh,</hi> were ſlightly Guarded, whereupon they ſent for Captain <hi>Henry Smith,</hi> and Captain <hi>Robert Corry,</hi> who Quartred at <hi>Newport</hi> Town, within four miles of them, theſe two Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains with their Companies, joyned the two Troops, marched in the night to <hi>Omagh,</hi> where they ſurpriſed, and brought off the Horſes belonging to two Troops of Dragoones, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97788:25"/>ſome black Cattle without oppoſition, the Enemy not dare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to obſtruct them, although in view.</p>
            <p>Soon after this, we had an Account of the miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition the poor Inhabitants of the City of <hi>Londou Derry</hi> were in, and that for want of Proviſions, they would be forced to deliver up that place, a Dogs head and Pluck at that time (as we were aſſured) yeilding two Shillings and ſix pence, all the Horſes they had being already eaten, with old Hides, Tallow, Starch, and what elſe of that nature, they could purchaſe; and knowing very well, that our ſafety and ſtanding depended much upon that place, for if <hi>Derry</hi> had been taken by the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> we could not poſſibly hold out againſt the whole power of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation having ſo ſmall a quantity of Ammunition, ſo few Arms; no Cannon; and a Town weakly fortified; we therefore reſolved to ſee if poſſible we could any way relieve <hi>Derry,</hi> we did not believe our ſelves able to raiſe the Seige; nay there were we reſolved to periſh in the attempt; all we propoſed to our ſelves, was to march with what Proviſions we could down to the Eaſt ſide of <hi>Derry</hi> River, oppoſite to the City, and there beat up the Enemies quarter, <hi>viz.</hi> Thoſe of them that lay on that ſide; for their Army lay on the Weſt ſide of the River, which is the ſide the City is on; ſo to Convoy Proviſions into Town, and to leave them ſome Horſe, the better to aſſiſt their Sallies; but indeed we reſolved, when come to that length, that if they thought it adviſable, all to paſs the River and give the Enemy a Bruſh.</p>
            <p>To which purpoſe what force we could make, were drawn out, and the Governor would himſelf march in the head of them, although contrary to the advice and deſire of all the Party; we doubted not the ſecurity of the Town, leaving Lieutenant Col. <hi>Lloyde</hi> there, but rather our own ſucceſs under the Governors conduct; having never done any thing to our Advantage, where Lieutenant Col. <hi>Lloyde</hi> was wanting; and where the Lieutenant Col. Commanded, we never failed in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97788:26"/>accompliſhing what we deſigned; we marched that night to <hi>Trillicke</hi> nine miles; next day in the afternoon, towards <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh</hi> upon our march, there were ſome free Booters, that ſcoured on before knocked on the head, amongſt them one Mr. <hi>Rowland Betty</hi> a very honeſt Gentleman, who was ſhot dead off his Horſe; as we marched the Country came into us, one all hands both Horſe and Foot, what <hi>Brittiſh</hi> were in it, ſo that by the time we came to <hi>Omagh,</hi> we were double the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber we were when leaving <hi>Iniskilling;</hi> indeed we had but a ſmall quantity of Powder, yet enough to have carried us to <hi>Derry,</hi> where we might have been plentifully ſupplyed; we lay that night within a mile of <hi>Omagh:</hi> The Enemy upon our approach, burnt all the Houſes, upon or near the Road; next morning we marched into the Town, there being no Garriſon ſave what lay in a Houſe of Captain <hi>Marvins,</hi> at the end of the Town, the Houſe was pretty ſtrong, with a Banewall clear round it; we drew up our Foot in view, and within ſhot of the Enemies Fortification; our advance Guard of Foot, led by Captain <hi>Atchiſon,</hi> and Captain <hi>Galbreth,</hi> Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed themſelves of ſeveral Gardings, Ditches, and Walls of Houſes that the Enemy had burnt, which lay near Captain <hi>Marvins</hi> Houſe, ſo fired at the Walls; the Enemy fireing out very thick, both at them and the body of Foot that ſtood in view of them; there was a Trumpet ſent down, with a Summons to Surrender the Houſe; they ſent back an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in Wrighting, that they knew no authority we had either to bear Arms, or Summon them; therefore they would defend that place, unleſs they ſee an order from King <hi>James</hi> to the contrary, and withal told the Trumpet to come no more with ſuch Meſſages, elſe they would wellcome him with their Firelockes.</p>
            <p>This while ſome of our Horſe ſcouting abroad, brought in five Priſoners, taken upon the Road leading from <hi>Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganan</hi> to <hi>Omagh,</hi> who when examined told us that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Lord <hi>Clankarty,</hi> who lay at <hi>Donganan</hi> the night
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97788:26"/>before, upon his march with two Regiments of Foot, one of Horſe, and one of Dragoons, to reinforce the Camp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Derry,</hi> and that he would be at <hi>Omagh</hi> by three of the Clock in the afternoon.</p>
            <p>Its true we very well knew e're our coming abroad that Colonel <hi>Sarsfield</hi> lay in Sir <hi>William Gores</hi> Deer Park; and did not know but he might attack <hi>Iniskilling</hi> in our abſence, but when the intelligence was given us, of the Lord <hi>Clankar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> approach, which was very true, there was a Counſel of War call'd, to ſe what was fit to be done; and finding that we had not one ounce of Proviſion for our ſelves, much leſs to relieve our Friends in <hi>Derry,</hi> there not being one Hoof driven along with us, by whoſe miſtake I wont ſay; and that <hi>Clankarty</hi> coming in our Rear, we might precipitate our ſelves into the ſame Straights that <hi>Derry</hi> lay under, unleſs we could be aſſured of beating the whole Army that lay before it, and that immediately too, which we could not imagin our ſelves capable of performing, therefore upon theſe grounds it was thought more adviſeable, to return to <hi>Iniskilling;</hi> but had we brought Proviſions along with us to have put into <hi>Derry,</hi> and ſuſtained our ſelves while our return, all the whole par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were extreamly willing to have gone the length of <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> with the Proviſions, had there been any; and when <hi>Derry</hi> had been ſupplied, to have retreated the Mountain way, and ſhunned engaging King <hi>James</hi>'s Army; but in place of that as I told you before we had not a Morſel for our ſelves, when we had marched but Eighteen miles, yet we had two and twenty more, e're we could come at <hi>Derry</hi> the neareſt way; ſo we retreated meanly to <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any thing, we might have burnt <hi>Omagh,</hi> but out of the value we had for Captain <hi>Marvin,</hi> the worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that owed it; although it was a relief to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my we forbore; but they burnt it to the ground, at their going off from the Seige of <hi>Derry,</hi> ſo it had been the ſame thing to Captain <hi>Marvin.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:97788:27"/>
            <p>Our next Expedition was under our former conducter Col <hi>Lloyde,</hi> which proved more Succeſsful, and Advantagious to us, as all his undertakings did, for the ſixteenth of <hi>June,</hi> we received intelligence from Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Creighton</hi> out of <hi>Crum</hi> Caſtle; and Captain <hi>William Wiſhart</hi> (who at his own Charge, had Raiſed and Armed a brave Troop of Horſe, and maintained them upon the Frontiers of our Country, during all our Troubles) that there was a powerful party of the Enemy, come the length of <hi>Belturbet,</hi> under whoſe Command they knew not, but did believe they would ſoon be with us; upon which intelligence, Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyde,</hi> with what ſtrength we could make, both Horſe and Foot marched that very night, with a reſolution of being in with the Enemy are they could have notice of our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, but coming to <hi>Liſnaskey</hi> Ten miles from <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> that night and near half way to <hi>Belturbet,</hi> next morning was ſo great a Rain, continuing all day, that we could not poſſibly march, and keep our Armes dry; our Cloaths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but ordinary: The Eighteen, we marched very early up to <hi>Newtown Buttler,</hi> where we drew up, to allow the Men to eat ſomething; upon our halt, intelligence was brought us by one <hi>Vitch</hi> who had come from <hi>Belturbet,</hi> that the party there was Commanded by one <hi>Brigadeer Sutherland,</hi> who he ſaid had intelligence ſent him of our march, very early the day before, and that we were Fourteen or Fifteen Thouſand men; ſo that he was marched off with all ſpeed towards <hi>Managhan,</hi> with moſt of his Men, and two peece of Canon, leaving a ſmall party at <hi>Belturbet,</hi> for defence of that place; Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyde</hi> upon this notice, called the Officers immediatly together, where it was propoſed, whether we ſhould ſtrive to ingage <hi>Sutherland,</hi> or march directly to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbet;</hi> but a Troop of Horſe returning, that the Colonel had ſent upon the gallop to diſcover the Enemy, and giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſurance that by that time, they would be near <hi>Manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han,</hi> ſixteen miles from us, and that they marched very hard
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97788:27"/>and in great fear, having left ſome of their Buncarts and Carriages upon the Road, it was reſolved to march directly to <hi>Belturbet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Reſolve was immediately put in practice, Captain <hi>Vaghan</hi> and Capt. <hi>Galbreth</hi> marched with their Dragoons as an advance Guard, the Horſe followed; then Lieut. <hi>Mac Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick</hi> with his Company, conſiſting of an hundred Men, as the Advance Guard of Foot, Major <hi>Wood</hi>'s followed with eight pair of Colours, Capt. <hi>Francis Gore</hi> with fourteen pair, and in the Rear two Troops of Horſe. The Dragoons when they came within ſomething more than a mile of <hi>Belturbet,</hi> were beat back by the Enemies Dragoons who had lined the Hedges; but our Horſe coming up, and our Dragoons alighting taking the inſide of the Hedges, and our Horſe the Lane, they ſoon drove them from thence, purſuing them all the way, killing ſome of them e're they got to Town: Then theſe Dragoons that were routed, together with what of their Men were in Town, got all into the Church and Church-yard, our Horſe ſurrounding them at a diſtance to keep them in while the Foot would march up, who marched extream hard, having Expreſs upon Expreſs to haſten them, fearing leaſt the Enemy ſhould ſally, and ſo eſcape into the Woods; but the Foot coming up, the Enemy fired very hot from the Church-yard; ſome of our men getting into the Town fired out of the Houſes, and particularly from the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Dublin</hi>'s Houſe, which was high over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looking the Church-yard, from whence they wounded ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Enemy. The Lieutenant Colonel as ſoon as we were drawn up and ready to ſtorm, ſent a Trumpet with a Summons to ſurrender, and upon condition that their Lives ſhould be ſaved, the Officers not ſtripped, and allowed to keep Ten Pounds of money a man (but they had not Ten Pounds amongſt them all) they ſurrendered; Mr. <hi>Mac Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick</hi> was then commanded to enter the Fort, which he did, diſarming all the Officers, the private Souldiers grounding their Arms and marching clear of them, their Arms were
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97788:28"/>ſecured, themſelves taken to the Biſhop's Houſe, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber about three hundred, where they were ſtrip'd and kept Priſoners that Night; there was not a Bullet found about any of them, nor in their Arms, but what was chawed. The Officers, being ſixteen in number, one Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Scot,</hi> alias <hi>Albanagh,</hi> commanding in chief, were put into another Houſe under a Guard.</p>
            <p>We got in this Expedition near ſeven hundred new Arms, (brought to arm a Regiment to be new raiſed) beſides what the Souldiers had that were taken Priſoners, two large Barrels of Gun-powder, fifty three Horſes with their Accoutrements, about twenty Tuns of Proviſion, <hi>viz.</hi> Bread, Flower, Wheat, Malt, and the like, which together with the Officers taken Priſoners, were ſent by Water to <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> the private men by Land there were near two hundred turned off and allowed to eſcape together with the Women and Children, the reſt were taken to <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> where for their meat they were made to work at the Fort we were then a building.</p>
            <p>The Arms and Powder here got did us a ſingular kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, both arming our men that wanted before, and adding to our number ſeveral that did no Duty for want of Arms, beſides an additional ſtore of Powder, which we had better Supplies of very ſuddenly after, and unexpectedly, on this manner.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of <hi>July</hi> we received a Letter from one Mr. <hi>Brown,</hi> Chaplain of the <hi>Bonadventure,</hi> a Frigot ſent about from <hi>Lough Sully</hi> near <hi>Derry</hi> to <hi>Killibeggs,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Captain <hi>Hobſon,</hi> adviſing us that Major General <hi>Kirk</hi> was there with ſome Forces ſent from <hi>England</hi> to ſupply that Gariſon with Proviſions, and to raiſe that Siege if poſſible, therefore deſired to know what condition we were in, or if we wanted any thing that he was capable of ſupplying us with, and deſired that ſome of the Townſmen might be ſent to give them aſſurance of our ſtate; for it was then
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97788:28"/>confidently reported by the Iriſh Army, as it had been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally times before, that <hi>Iniskilling</hi> vvas taken and all put to the Sword that was in it.</p>
            <p>I preſume any man will believe this was the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable News that ever we had in our Lives, hearing at laſt that <hi>England</hi> had us in their minds; for ſeveral times before in the night we aſſembled, making of Bonfires, and firing of Vollies, (which was more than we could well ſpair of Ammunition) and drinking King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Health; this did amuſe the Enemy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded them ſeveral times to believe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were landed to our aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Upon the Receit of Mr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Letter Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyde</hi> was ſent to give Captain <hi>Hobſon</hi> a particular account vvhat ſtate and condition we vvere in, and with him ſome Troops and Companies of Foot to guard what Ammunition or Arms vve ſhould receive. When our Officers vvent on board they were very kindly received and treated by Captain <hi>Hobſon;</hi> and after giving him the ſtate of our Affairs he ſent us thirty barrels of Gun-powder, and ſome few Fire-locks, and aſſured Colonel <hi>Lloyde</hi> that we ſhould be very ſoon relieved from <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A vvhile before this the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> vvho kept a flying Army moſt of the time <hi>Derry</hi> was beſieged, vvhich they vvere conſtrained to do fearing always that <hi>Iniskilling</hi>-men would fall in upon their Camp, marched over <hi>Barnſmore</hi> and came upon <hi>Dumigall</hi> early in the morning, the Garriſon held out for us, and e're our men could be in a readineſs, vvho were commanded by Captain <hi>Edward Johnſton</hi> and Capt. <hi>Hugh Cudwell,</hi> a Son of Sir <hi>James Cudwell's,</hi> the Enemy was in the Town; our men were forced to betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Caſtle, from vvhence they fired ſo briskly upon the Enemy, killing ſeveral of them, that they immediately retreated, burning the Town e're they went off, yet our men kept that Garriſon during the vvhole Troubles.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:97788:29"/>
            <p>About the fourth of <hi>June</hi> the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> vvith his flying Army, having joyned to him Brigadeer <hi>Sutherland</hi> with what forces he took off from <hi>Belturbet,</hi> all conſiſting of about ſix Regiments of Foot, four Regiments of Dragoons, and two of Horſe came toward <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> we had intelligence of his approach, and marched out to meet him; but e're vve could come up, he retreated to <hi>Trillicke,</hi> burning Mr. <hi>Andrew Hamilton</hi>'s Houſe upon his Retreat. Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> perhaps did imagine that this hardſhip vvas ſhewn him for being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in bringing off the Dragoon-Horſes from <hi>Omagh</hi> before-mentioned: I could give the Reaſons of his being ſo dealt by, and I do verily believe had they got him they would have put him to death; but he is now dead, and I carry a regard to his Reputation, therefore deſire to be excuſed if I ſay no more.</p>
            <p>During the Dukes incamping at <hi>Trillicke,</hi> we kept ſtrong Guards upon the Road, ſometimes skirmiſhing with parties of his Men. But upon the thirteenth of <hi>July,</hi> he with his whole Party came on towards <hi>Iniskilling;</hi> before day in the morning our Scouts bringing certain intelligence of his approach, all got to Arms, the Governour getting on Horſeback.</p>
            <p>Here I cannot but obſerve, that Mr. <hi>Andrew Hamilton</hi> in his Relation of this Paſſage, is either forgetful, or hath been miſinformed, where he ſays that the Governour ſent two Companies to a Paſs near the Mill of <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> by which the Dukes Army muſt paſs before they could come near the Town, and might have been eaſily defended by a few men; when in the mean time the Governour was getting the reſt of his men together to ſecond them, but the two Companies coming to the Mill and ſeeing no Enemy near, after ſome ſtay they advanced near a mile further than their Poſt, and coming to a hallow betwixt two Hills, were on a ſudden ſurprized with the whole Body of the Enemies Horſe and Dragoons coming upon them.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:97788:29"/>
            <p>Theſe are Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s words, I am ſorry he ſhould have been ſo miſinformed, for when this Ingagement was, (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not an Eye-witneſh, nor Actor in it) he was in the <hi>Lough</hi> of <hi>Derry,</hi> as will appear hereafter. But now to the Truth of the Action, which was thus:</p>
            <p>As I ſaid before, We having the Aſſurance of the Enemies Approach, by our Scouts, we betook our ſelves to Arms; the Governour being on Horſe-back, came to L. <hi>Mat-Carmick,</hi> he having the Company under his Command drawn up in the Street earlier than others were got to Arms, and deſired the Lieutenant that he would immediately march his Company and make good <hi>Corngrad-Houſe;</hi> this Houſe ſtands upon a Hill within a quarter of a Mile of the Town, near to the Rode the Enemy were to march, being but a thatched Houſe, and no way tonable, altho invironed with a Bane Wall, ſave the ſide the Houſe ſtood on; but no Port-holes for the Men to fire out at, and too high by much to fire over, ſo that we could not poſſibly annoy the Enemy out of it; and they with the firing one Piſtol might ſet the Houſe on fire, the whole Court being full of Thatch and Straw, the Men could not eſcape being burnt alive: He therefore retreated to the Mill of <hi>Inniskillin,</hi> (without Command) being a very ſtrait Paſs, and under the Cannon-ſhot from the Fort, there poſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Men. The Governour a while after, came up with two Troops of Horſe, and 30 Foot of Capt. <hi>Hudſon</hi>'s Company; the Horſe commanded by Capt. <hi>Hugh Montgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Francis King;</hi> the 30 Foot by Lieut. <hi>Robert Starlin,</hi> and Enſign <hi>Williams:</hi> The Governour called L. <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Carmick,</hi> and taking him by the Hand, deſired that he would join Lieut. <hi>Starlin,</hi> and lead on the Foot as far as the Hedg led upon the left Hand of the High-way towards the Enemy, telling him, that theſe two Troops were going to Charge. The Lieutenant replied, that the Foot were too ſmall a Party, being in all but 102 Men, whereof the third part were Pikes, which ſignified nothing to the Lining of the Hedg, and that he had no great Confidence in the Horſe,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97788:30"/>but did believe they would deſert him if engaged. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour ſwore he would warrant the Horſe not fly one foot, and that he would ſend a powerful Party of Foot ſhould be there as ſoon as they. The Lieutenant anſwered, that he would go every ſtep as far as commanded, if he died; but deſired the Governour to mind his Promiſe in ſending a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Supply of Foot, ſo marched on the Men: He meeting one Lieut. <hi>Campbel</hi> on Horſe-back, who told him, the Enemy were at Hand: He deſired him to poſt after the Governour, and mind him to ſend more Foot. And again, meeting Capt. <hi>Webſter</hi> on Horſe-back, who had been viewing the Enemy, he prevailed with him to ride hard after the Governour, and mind him of his Promiſe in ſending more Men. When Lieut. <hi>Campbel</hi> got up to the Governour, he was got into the Town, forgetting or neglecting to ſend away Reinforcement, altho all the way as he went was full of armed Men, and more in the Fort than it could well contain; Lieut. <hi>Campbel</hi> telling him, that <hi>Mac-Carmick</hi> was cloſe upon the Enemy, and muſt immediately Ingage: His Anſwer was, Let them Ingage, he would ſend Boats to bring them off; and when Capt. <hi>Web<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> came up to him, he was got into the Caſtle of <hi>Inniskillin;</hi> he putting him in mind of his Promiſe of ſending ſpeedy Supplies, the Governour bid <hi>Webſter</hi> to go and command one Capt. <hi>Henry Smith,</hi> who was marching his Company to <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorah</hi>-Caſtle, upon the other ſide of the <hi>Lough,</hi> above two miles from us, to march back again to our Relief; I ſay, our Relief, becauſe I was in the Action, and had reaſon to know every Circumſtance of it: And whereas Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> ſays, the Foot were ſurprized in a Bottom betwixt two Hills, with the whole Body of the Enemies Horſe and Dragoons, it is a great miſtake, for we were upon a Hill in full view of the Enemy, and ſaw every ſtep they made towards us; ſo that there was no ſurprize, neither did their whole Body move, only 600 Dragoons on Foot, and two Troops of Horſe; when they came up, we fired upon them ſo hotly, killing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of them, that the Dragoons turned their Backs and fled,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97788:30"/>leaving their Colonel, <hi>viz. Lutterell,</hi> behind them: Then our Horſe, without firing one Shot, as if they had deſigned to invite the Enemy to a ſecond Charge upon the Foot, ran clear away to give them the better opportunity: Which <hi>Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terell</hi> ſeeing, called out aloud, <hi>They run, they run; their Horſe are fled.</hi> The Dragoons facing about, and ſeeing our Horſe fled, came on again, where we had a ſharp Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but two Troops of their Horſe charging up, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounding us, we were cut to pieces. We loſt in this Action Enſign <hi>Williams,</hi> with above fifty private Men; Capt. <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Lieut. <hi>Mac-Carmick,</hi> (who had his eldeſt Son killed by his ſide) Enſign <hi>Picking,</hi> two Sergeants, and 20 private Men taken Priſoners, and carried along with the Enemy.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> ſays, that by the time we were broke, the Governour was on his way to our Relief, which cauſed the Duke's ſuddain Retreat; whereas there was no ſuch thing, for he ne'r came one ſtep towards it, neither ſent one Man; it was ſo far from that, he went, as I ſaid before, ſtrait to <hi>Inniskillin</hi>-Caſtle; and one Lieut. <hi>Fort,</hi> a Lieutenant of Horſe, meeting him, told him there was a Party of Horſe willing to go on to ſecond us, if he would appoint who ſhould Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them. The Governour's Anſwer was very peeviſh; <hi>Don't you ſee the Enemy before you? Can't you go and fight?</hi> Lieut. <hi>Fort</hi> replied, <hi>If that be your Anſwer, I'll fight none to day.</hi> Indeed Capt. <hi>Atkinſon,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Robert Corry,</hi> with their Companies, when they heard us engaged, and ſee our Horſe fly, came from the Fort, without Command, to our Relief; but were too late, for the Action was over, and the Enemy retreated before they could come up.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> likewiſe ſays, That the two Companies go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beyond their Poſt, was the cauſe of burning Capt. <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s Houſe, and ſeveral Houſes about the Town; whereas all the Houſes that were burnt near the Town, were burnt in our view e're the Ingagement, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Paul Danes</hi> the then Provoſt of our Town, and Mr. <hi>Lautournal</hi>'s, and Capt. <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s Houſe was not burnt while three a Clock in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97788:31"/>by which time the Enemy were in their Camp nine Miles off. I admire that Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> ſpeaks nothing of the two Troops that were to ſecond the Foot going beyond their Poſts; he ſays, they wheeled off without fighting. Now if they ſtood at this Paſs at the Millen he ſpeaks of, there was no need of their wheeling from thence, for the Millen was under the Cannon-ſhot from the Fort, and the Enemy never came within Cannon-ſhot of the Millen, nor ſo much as once in ſight of it; if they went on with the Foot, ſure if the Foot diſobeyed Command, they did the like, which he mentions not; but perhaps their running away ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated their Crime.</p>
            <p>Now by what has been ſaid, You may ſee it was not any fault in theſe that were commanded to line the Hedge, (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs fighting bravely againſt an Enemy be a Fault) for they went not one Step further than they were commanded; and would have routed the Enemy, had the Horſe but ſtood by and look'd at them; but in place of that, or doing as Men ought to do, they baſely ran away; which encouraged the Enemy to come on again, after they were once put to the Retreat.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> likewiſe, ſays, That we were the only Priſoners that were taken, and received Quarter by any of the Iriſh Army, and not murdered after; which he attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bures wholly to the Governour's writing a threatning Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Duke, that he would be revenged on the Priſoners then in his hands, if they offered us any Violence. I know nothing of the Governour's writing any ſuch Letter; but this I am ſure of (although I do not ſpeak this in favour of the Iriſh, for I hate them, and have as much Reaſon for it as any Man) that when I was taken Priſoner by one <hi>Burke</hi> a Captain of Horſe, the ſame that had formerly taken Sir <hi>Thomas Suthwell</hi> and his Party Priſoners, he immediately brought me to the Duke of <hi>Berwick;</hi> where I told the Duke, that it was his fortune to get the better of our ſmall Party that Morning, and that his Officers had been pleaſed to give
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97788:31"/>ſome of us Quarters, which I hoped he would confirm: he anſwered, We ſhould have very good Quarters, and call'd out twice or thrice as loud as could, that no Man upon pain of Death, ſhould touch a Priſoner, or take any thing that he had from him, and gave particular Orders to Capt. <hi>Burke,</hi> to command the Guard to have a particular Care of us: and I am ſure this was before the Governour could write, or know that we were Priſoners. And while we were kept Priſoners, which was near three Weeks, (and had been there ſtill for ought I know for all our Governour, had not Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> releaſed us) we were kindly dealt by, and well provided for; here is the truth of the whole Action: But we now found the want of Lieut. Col. <hi>Lloyd,</hi> our brave and vigilant Conducter, for had he been with us, who was now at <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhannon,</hi> we had undoubtedly routed the Duke and his Army to <hi>Derry</hi> Camp; for Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi> was a good Sort of Man, he was vigilant, careful, active, of a great Soul, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſerving, ſlipp'd no Opportunity that offered to gain his End; and beſides, a Man of unwearied Induſtry, and good Intelligence, and for his Perſonal Valour; few went beyond him.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> ſays, That the Duke next day after this Engagement, went to the Camp near <hi>Derry;</hi> whereas the Duke ſtirred not from <hi>Frillick</hi> next day; indeed upon <hi>Monday</hi> following, he marched as far as <hi>Omagh,</hi> upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> to <hi>Caſtleſin,</hi> upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> to a Deer-Park called <hi>Cavan,</hi> which is but three Miles from <hi>Caſtleſin,</hi> where he left his Horſe and Foot; but he himſelf with a Party of Dragoons went upon <hi>Friday</hi> near to <hi>Lutterkeny,</hi> on <hi>Saturday</hi> to <hi>Rath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mollan,</hi> where he had an Engagement with ſome of Maj. Gen. <hi>Kirk</hi>'s Men, and was worſted; upon <hi>Sunday</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Park at <hi>Cavan,</hi> and there continued while the Siege of <hi>Derry</hi> roſe; ſo that he never went near that Camp after leaving <hi>Inniskillin.</hi> This I certainly know, being Priſoner with him, and marched along upon foot to all theſe Places.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:97788:32"/>
            <p>Soon after this Sir <hi>Gerrard Ervin</hi> joined with us, and headed our Horſe in an Expedition againſt Col. <hi>Sarsfield,</hi> who had removed from Sir <hi>William Gore</hi>'s Deer-Park, and lay encamp'd at a place called <hi>Bendruſe,</hi> betwixt <hi>Balliſhannon</hi> and <hi>Sligo</hi> upon the Sea-ſide, where he had poſted himſelf ſo advantageouſly, and ſo well flanked with Cannon, that our Men could not move him; nor he durſt not draw out to engage us, although many more in Number than we were; ſo we marched back to <hi>Inniskillin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We began now to underſtand, though we doubted Sir <hi>Gerrard Ervin</hi> in the beginning, that he had been no bad Friend to us, but rather had been a Means of hindring any of the Iriſh Army coming againſt <hi>Inniskillin</hi> while we recovered Strength, and were pretty able to cope with them; but the Methods he took for doing this cauſed our Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for he wanting Arms and Ammunition in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and likewiſe knowing it was our want alſo; he made application to the Government, who gave him compleat Arms and Accouterments for a hundred Horſe, with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mmunition, believing he would have reduced <hi>Inniskillin</hi> to their Obedience; whereas his Reſolution was, if he had got his Arms ſafe down, to have joined and declared himſelf publickly for us, but the County of <hi>Cavan</hi> Gentlemen, ſeized them upon the Road, and took them all from Sir <hi>Gerrard,</hi> ſo rendred him incapable of arming his Men, and appearing as he would; this was the cauſe of his ſo long lying quiet, yet he fortified his Houſe very well in the beginning of our trouble; and when the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> came to encamp at <hi>Frillick,</hi> he demanded his Houſe to have placed a Gariſon in it, which Sir <hi>Gerrard</hi> abſolutely refuſed. After the Duke's going off from <hi>Frillick,</hi> he raiſed a good Troop of Horſe, with which he marched to <hi>Dundalk</hi> Camp, doing good Service there under General <hi>Schonberg,</hi> and was in very much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and eſteem; but contracted a Fever before the raiſing of that Camp, and there died.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:97788:32"/>
            <p>During Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi>'s ſtay at <hi>Balliſhannon,</hi> he ſent Maj. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> by Sea about to the <hi>Lough</hi> of <hi>Derry</hi> to ſatisfy Maj. Gen: <hi>Kirk</hi> what Condition <hi>Inniskillin</hi> was in, and to ſollicit for Arms, Ammunition, and Commiſſions. When the Maj. Gen. knew how things were with us, he ſent us Arms and Ammunition, Bullets and Match, with Commiſſions for a Regiment of Horſe conſiſting of 16 Troops, a Regiment of Dragoons of 12 Troops, 3 Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Foot each conſiſting of 18 Companies, and ſome very good Men for our Officers, <hi>viz. William Woolſely</hi> Col. of Horſe, and Commander in Chief; <hi>Will. Barry</hi> his Lieut. Colonel, and <hi>Charles Stone</hi> Major; <hi>James Winn</hi> Col. of Dragoons; and for the Foot, Col. <hi>Tiffany</hi> our Governour, and Col. <hi>Tho. Lloyd;</hi> for Aid Maj. General, Capt. <hi>Price;</hi> for Ingenier, Capt. <hi>H. Johnſton.</hi> The Officers came by Sea to <hi>Balliſhannon</hi> the 26th of <hi>July,</hi> from thence by Water to <hi>Inniskillin,</hi> where they landed the 28th to the great ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of all there; we having with a longing Deſire many a time pray'd for the landing of the Engliſh, and now when we ſee ſome of them come to our Aſſiſtance and Relief, it may be judged how much overjoyed we were.</p>
            <p>But they were no ſooner come, than they had Work cut out for them; for that very Night came an Expreſs from Lieut. Col. <hi>Creighton,</hi> giving an Account that Lieut. Gen. <hi>Mackarty</hi> was with an Army come before <hi>Crume,</hi> there forming a Camp to beſiege the Caſtle, and had brought Cannon with him to batter it: Next day came another Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, aſſuring us, that Lieut. Gen. <hi>Maskarty</hi> had made his Approaches very near the Caſtle, and play'd hard upon it with his Cannon. They therefore deſired we would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour their Relief, with what ſpeed we could; they having no Cannon in the Caſtle, only ſmall-ſhot, with which they killed ſeveral of the Enemy.</p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> returned anſwer, That he would endeavour to relieve them upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> following; and immediately ſent to <hi>Balliſhannon</hi> for what of our Forces were there that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97788:33"/>could be ſpared, who marched up to <hi>Inniskillin</hi> upon <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> the 30th of <hi>July,</hi> 20 long Miles, and next Morning 15 Miles e're they fought the Enemy. Which was on this Manner;</p>
            <p>Lieut. Col. <hi>Barry</hi> was ſent upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> to <hi>Liſnaskey,</hi> a Caſtle ten Miles from <hi>Inniskillin,</hi> and toward the Enemy, there to place a Gariſon if tenable, otherwiſe to burn it: but when he had viewed the Caſtle, he found it ſo out of order, that it was not fit to put a Gariſon in, neither could it ſignify much to the Enemy, ſo he left it without burning, and that Night lay Abroad with his Men; next Morning marched on two Miles further toward the Enemy, where his Scouts brought him Intelligence of the Enemies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach towards him: He not thinking it adviſable to engage with ſo ſmall a Party as he had with him, retreated towards <hi>Liſnaskey,</hi> but the Enemy preſt ſo hard that they diſordered ſeveral of our Men; and had not Lieut. Col. <hi>Barry</hi> ſeveral times faced about with a Troop or two of Horſe, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways put the Enemy to a ſtand to draw up, they had certainly routed us to <hi>Inniskillin;</hi> but our Horſe getting through a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver below one Mrs. <hi>Lenard</hi>'s, about a Mile from <hi>Liſnaskey,</hi> toward <hi>Inniskillin,</hi> at a very Boggy deep Paſs; and Capt. <hi>Malcome Caſhcart</hi> coming up with about 120 Foot: The Horſe by the Induſtry and Perſuaſion of Capt. <hi>Martin Armſtrong</hi> rallied; Capt. <hi>Caſhcart</hi> came to the Officers of Horſe, and promiſed that if they would ſtand by him, and not ſerve him and his Men as they had ſerved Lieut. <hi>Mac-Carmick,</hi> he would beat back the Enemy; and if they would not ſtand by him, to deal plainly with him. The Officers of Horſe proteſted that they would aſſiſt him, and not a Man of them would turn their Backs; upon which Capt. <hi>Caſhcart</hi> places an Ambuſh of about 18 or 20 Firelocks in a Thicket of Buſhes on the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Flank, as they muſt come on to charge, on the Enemies ſide of the River; commanding them not to fire a Shot while he, and they that were with him, firſt fired: then he ranked the remainder of his Men along the other Bank of the River,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97788:33"/>as much in Covert as he could. The Enemy by this time were come up, and ſeeing our Horſe Rally and draw up, and our Foot to make good the Paſs, reſolved to force it: To that purpoſe Col. <hi>Anthony Hamilton</hi> commanded a Regiment of Dragoons to alight; he led them on, firing very thick as they came on, while within forty Yards of the River; then Capt. <hi>Cathcart</hi> commanded his Men (who had not yet fired one ſhot) to fire; at which Volley they killed ſeveral of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and wounded Col. <hi>Hamilton:</hi> then theſe in Ambuſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe upon the Enemies Flank, fired, killing ſome of the Enemy. <hi>Hamilton</hi> being wounded, went off, ſending another Officer to command the Dragoons; but Capt. <hi>Cathcart</hi> plied them ſo warmly with his Shot, that Officer being killed, the Dragoons were commanded to face to the Right-about, to draw them further out of our Shot: But as ſoon as they fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, they ran for it; our Horſe and Foot immediately char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged through the River, which the Enemies Horſe perceiving, fled likewiſe; we had the purſuit of them three miles, all which way the Road was filled with their dead Bodies. By this time there were freſh Recruits of the Enemy coming up; which our Men perceiving, being weary with ſo vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a purſuit, retreated to the Mote of <hi>Liſnaskey,</hi> where they met Gol. <hi>Woolſely</hi> with the reſt of our Forces.</p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> returning Thanks for that Morning's Work, which was a good Introduction to gaining the Battel in the Afternoon, immediatly aſſembled the Officers to conſult what was farther fit to be done, telling, that their Reſolves muſt be ſpeedy, the Men that came along with him having made ſuch haſte up to the Relief of their Fellows, that ſcarce any of them had brought a Meal of Meat along with them, it was immediately concluded amongſt the Officers, that it was fit to go on; and the Queſtion put to the Souldiers, they unanimouſly cried out, to march and fight the Enemy, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they had never been accuſtomed, when they ſaw an Enemy, to turn their Backs, ſave the ill-managed Buſineſs at <hi>Omagh,</hi> and the run-away Horſe in the Ingagement with the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97788:34"/>Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> which was occaſioned by one Horſe-Officer. Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> finding the Men ſo willing to ingage the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, immediately formed the Foot into three Battalions; the Right and Left Wings led by Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi> (who never yet had failed in any thing he attempted) and Col. <hi>Tiffon,</hi> a worthy Gentleman, and an excellent Souldier; the main Body he led himſelf; the Horſe he ordered a Detachment for an Advance Guard, who marched on before at a little diſtance, ſome Troops to ſecond the Right and Left Wings; and the main Body of Horſe in the Rear, led on by the Lieut. Col. and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor; the Dragoons divided in two Parties to aſſiſt the Flanks; ſo marched on towards <hi>Newtown-Butler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lieut. Gen. <hi>Mac-Carty</hi> hearing of our Approach, drew off his Men and Cannon from <hi>Crum-Caſtle,</hi> near to a place called <hi>Newtown-Butler,</hi> betwixt it and <hi>Wattle-Bridg,</hi> where he po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted them very advantagiouſly; his Cannon in a Lane, facing a narrow Paſs through a Bog, that not above one Horſe could could come abreaſt; his Foot upon the Right and Left of the Lane, all under Covert, that not a Man of them could be ſeen ſave thoſe that were about the Cannon; his Horſe upon the Right of all, drawn up upon a Hill.</p>
            <p>When we had marched within half a mile of <hi>Newtown-Butler,</hi> we diſcovered ſome of the Enemy drawn up on a Hill before us; ſo that the Foot upon both Wings marched through a Bog to come in with the Enemy; the Horſe were forced to keep the Cauſway, which was but narrow; and Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> with the Body moved ſlowly on: The Enemy fired very hard, but before we came in ſhot of them, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated orderly: We advanced apace, having command not to break our Ranks. As the Enemy retreated through <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town-Butler,</hi> (which they did very orderly, firing always in the Rear as they went off) they ſet the Town on fire, and ſo went to their main Body. When we marched up near them, our Pikes and Colours were left in a Body by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, being near a third part of our Number, and only the Fire-arms marched on as formerly, taking the Bog upon the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97788:34"/>Right and Left Hand of the Road, the Horſe not being able to advance, by reaſon of the narrowneſs of the Road, and the Enemies Cannon playing ſo hard upon them. When our Foot were advanced through the Bog, the Enemy fired ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream thick upon our Men, notwithſtanding we could not ſee a Man of them; but when we came cloſe upon them, we fell a firing where we ſaw their Smoke riſe, and ſoon was in with them, beating them out of their Covert, killing many of them; our Foot immediately ſeized their Cannon, where one luſty Man that formerly had belonged to my Lord <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> finding one Fellow with a Hatchet, repairing ſomewhat about the Cannon, ſnatch'd the Hatchet out of his Hand, and laid ſo well about him, that in the twinkling of an Eye he killed ſeven or eight of thoſe that were guarding the Cannon, ſome with the Edg of the Hatchet, and ſome with the Head of it; our Horſe ſeeing their Cannon ſeized, charged eagerly through the Paſs; which their Horſe perceiving, wheeled off and fled amain towards <hi>Wattle-Bridg;</hi> their Foot betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Bogs, moſt of them throwing away their Arms; our Horſe purſued the Enemies near <hi>Cavan,</hi> which is about ten miles from the Place of Battel; but the way being ſo narrow, leading through very great Bogs, they could do the Enemy little Prejudice; but what they did not do, our Foot made up, for they were as good of Foot as the Enemy, ſlaying abundance of them in the purſuit; and many took the <hi>Lough</hi> and were drowned, for they took the Water in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts, eſpecially near <hi>Wattle-Bridg,</hi> where ſix or ſeven hundred of them in a Body thought to have eſcaped: but our Horſe having left a good Guard to prevent their eſcaping that way, the Enemy drew up in order in a Meadow near the Bridg, and marched briskly towards the Horſe as if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to force their Paſſage over; but ſome of our Foot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, and our Horſe charging down upon them, they, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out firing, (many of them having thrown away their Arms before) all in a Body took the Water together, where they every Man died ſave one that ſwam through. Their Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant-General,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97788:35"/>after their Cannon was ſeized, and one Capt. <hi>George Cooper</hi> with a Party of Firelocks left to guard them, charged in upon the Cannon, with a ſmall Party of Horſe with him, but our Men ſoon brought him down, killing his Horſe; but by the goodneſs of his Armour he eſcaped, having received ſeveral Shots, ſome whereof upon his Armour, one through the right Thigh, one in at his left Loin, through the lower part of the Back-bone, and out at the right Thigh, and one in the Groin, which would certainly have killed him had it not been for his Watch, which the Bullet beat all to pieces; and the Wheels of the Watch cut the Bullet into many parts, whereof one entred his Groin a little; ſo had Quarter given him, and the others that were with him. Our Men followed the Purſuit all that Night, and till near ten of the Clock next Day; by which time they had ſcarce left any alive that fled towards the <hi>Lough.</hi> Upon their return, they gleaned up ſeveral amongſt the Buſhes that they gave Quarter to.</p>
            <p>Lieut. Gen. <hi>Mac-Carty,</hi> and ſome of the Officers, were ſent to <hi>Inniskillin</hi> by Water, the other Priſoners by Land, to the number of 300 and odd. Their whole Party was reputed to conſiſt of 6000 Men, and theſe the Choice of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in that Kingdom, &amp; the beſt fitted-out Army with all things neceſſary; but we could never learn that 2000 of them got off. We took ſeven Cannon, 12 or 13 Barrels of Powder, all their Colours, Drums, and abundance of Arms, with the Pillage of their whole Camp, and ſeveral Carts and Waggons. When their General was taken, altho he had no Money in his Pockets, there was a Letter found in them writ from Col. <hi>Sarsfield,</hi> two or three days before, acquainting, that he lay near <hi>Inniskillin,</hi> attending his Lordſhip's Motion; that if his Lordſhip and the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> would attaque <hi>Inniskilling</hi> on the Eaſt, he with thoſe under his Command, were ready to attaque it on the Weſt. But here you ſee, that by the great and never-fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mercy and Providence of God, we were delivered from them, and they prevented of their Deſign, and received from a handful of Men, not without a Miracle, that which they
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97788:35"/>came with a Reſolution to give others. Our Loſs being ſo ſmall in this Action, that we had but one Capt. <hi>Corry</hi> loſt, and he ſuppoſed to be killed by his own Men; and one Cornet <hi>Bell,</hi> with not half a ſcore private Men, and very few wounded.</p>
            <p>This Action gave the greateſt blow to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> that ever they had met with, for their whole Dependance was in a manner upon this Part of their Army, being ſo brave Men, ſo well fitted in every thing neceſſary, (ſave Courage) and having ſo excellent a General as they looked upon Lieut. Gen. <hi>Mac-Carty</hi> to be.</p>
            <p>Next day we returned to <hi>Inniskillin,</hi> where Lieut. Gen. <hi>Mac-Carty</hi> deſired to have liberty of ſending to K. <hi>James,</hi> to acquaint him vvhat Condition he was in; which was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him. The King ſent one Dr. <hi>Connor</hi> a Phyſician, and Mr. <hi>Huben</hi> a Chyrurgeon, to attend him, vvith Money, Wines, and other Neceſſaries fit for one in his Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, alſo Monies to the other Officers taken with him.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Friday</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> we marched towards <hi>Balliſhannon,</hi> with a Reſolution to Ingage Col. <hi>Sarsfield</hi> who lay ſtill at <hi>Bandruſe</hi> upon the Sea-ſide: But as we marched, we met an Expreſs ſent by Capt. <hi>Folliot,</hi> giving an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that Col. <hi>Sarsfield</hi> hearing of Lieut. Gen. <hi>Mac-Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>'s Defeat, had raiſed his Camp and retreated to <hi>Sligo;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo telling us, that the Arms and Ammunition ſent by Maj. Gen. <hi>Kirk,</hi> were landed at <hi>Balliſhannon.</hi> Upon this Col. <hi>Tiffon,</hi> and Lieut. Col. <hi>Gore,</hi> with a Party of Horſe and Foot, were ſent to <hi>Balliſhannon,</hi> to ſecure that Place in caſe <hi>Sarsfield</hi> ſhould return and attempt any thing againſt it: As alſo to take care in tranſmitting the Arms &amp; Ammunition to <hi>Inniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killin:</hi> The reſt of our Men marched back to <hi>Inniskillin,</hi> where the certainty of the Iriſh Army marching from <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and burning the whole Country as they went off, was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured them; for our Men that were taken and kept Priſoners by the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> being now by Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, returned Home, who had ſeen the Iriſh Army march off.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:97788:36"/>
            <p>Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> upon this Intelligence ſent a Troop of Horſe, under the Command of Lieut. <hi>William Charlton,</hi> to obſerve the Enemies Motion in their March, fearing leſt they might make Incurſion into our Countrey; but he going as far as <hi>Caſtle-Caulfield,</hi> ſaw the Rear of their Army paſs that Place, which is within ſeven Miles of <hi>Charlemont,</hi> near 30 from us, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and gave that Account.</p>
            <p>We now having Quiet on all Hands from the Attempts of our watchful Enemies, ſet a Day apart, as it was our Duty, to return Thanks to the great God of Heaven, who had manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted his Power in our Weakneſs, and ſo miraculouſly delivered us, beyond all Human Probability, being but a handful, out of the Hands and Power of our numerous and mercileſs Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this Maj. General <hi>Kirk</hi> ſent to Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> for 500 Horſe and 200 Dragoons, for the more ſafe marching the Foot, under his Command to join D. <hi>Schonberg,</hi> who was landed at <hi>Carickfergus;</hi> and deſired likewiſe that our Men ſhould take 200 of the Iriſh Priſoners down to <hi>Derry</hi> to aſſiſt the poor People there in cleanſing the Town, and emptying the Store-ſhips. Our Horſe and Dragoons marched down ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Maj. General's Order, taking the 200 Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners with them. Upon our Mens arrival, the Maj. General march'd to join the Duke by the way of <hi>Colraine,</hi> and came to <hi>Carickfergus</hi> without any Oppoſition.</p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Sarsfield</hi> after his leaving <hi>Bandruſe,</hi> ſtayed not long at <hi>Sligo;</hi> for Col. <hi>Tiffany</hi> reſolving to have him out of that, not liking his Neighbourhood, ſends Lieut. Col. <hi>Gore</hi> with a Party of Horſe and Foot to ſcour the Country as near <hi>Sligo</hi> as they could, and if poſſible, to diſcover what Strength <hi>Sarsfield</hi> might be of, and how poſted. Lieut. Col. <hi>Gore</hi> upon his march, takes an Iriſh-man Priſoner, who he ſet at liberty again, deſignedly to amuſe the Enemy, telling him that all the Forces that Maj. Gen. <hi>Kirk</hi> had brought out of <hi>England</hi> together with <hi>Derry</hi> and <hi>Inniskillin</hi> Men, were marching to fall in upon <hi>Sligo:</hi> This ſo alarm'd the Country
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97788:36"/>that they all ran with their Cattle to <hi>Roſcommon, Galloway,</hi> or <hi>Athlone,</hi> and the Army under <hi>Sarsfield</hi> did the like, taking little or nothing with them. <hi>Sarsfield</hi> being forced to follow, ſo Lieut. Col. <hi>Gore</hi> march'd into <hi>Sligo</hi> without Oppoſition, getting there ſeveral of the Enemies Cannon, and other things they had left behind.</p>
            <p>In <hi>September,</hi> D. <hi>Schonberg</hi> commands Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> with all the Horſe belonging to <hi>Inniskillin</hi> (Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi>'s Troop ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) Col. <hi>Winn</hi>'s Dragoons, Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi>'s, and Col. <hi>Tif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fany</hi>'s Regiments of Foot, immediately to march to <hi>Dundalk</hi> Camp, which they did: Col. <hi>Woolſely</hi> firſt ſending Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi> with his own Troop of Horſe, and ſix Companies of Foot of Col. <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Regiment, with ſome of Sir <hi>Albert Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningham</hi>'s Dragoons to <hi>Sligo,</hi> for the Defence of that Place.</p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi> had not been long there, e're he received Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that the Enemy were drawing to a Body at <hi>Abby Boyle,</hi> a Town belonging to my Lord <hi>Kingſton,</hi> and as it was his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Inclination never to be idle, he reſolves to give them a Viſit, and if poſſible to prevent their getting to a Head; he to that purpoſe marched what Force he had from <hi>Sligo</hi> by <hi>Killowney,</hi> ſo to <hi>Ballinafad,</hi> and over the <hi>Curlues,</hi> with as much privacy as he could, marching in the Night, and falling down near <hi>Boyle</hi> in the Morning early, where he thought to have ſurprized the Town: but in the place of that he found the Enemy both Horſe and Foot drawn up in very good Order to receive him, and far exceeding his Number; he was not long e're he with his accuſtomed Fortitude engaged them, and as ſoon put them to the Rout, killing about 300 of their Foot, and ſeveral of their Horſe, who he had the Purſuit of near to <hi>Roſcommon.</hi> Upon this Victory he march'd immediately to <hi>James-town,</hi> where the Enemy had a Gariſon, and took it; together with Col. <hi>Mac-Donnel</hi>'s Houſe, a ſtrong Houſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Drumſnaw,</hi> near to <hi>James town:</hi> Here he got a vaſt Prey of black Cattle, Sheep and Horſes, with all the Growth of the Country. Col. <hi>Lloyd</hi> upon this ſends an Expreſs, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints D. <hi>Schonberg</hi> of his gaining ſo great a Part of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97788:37"/>Country, and deſires to know what to do, he having no Men to Gariſon theſe Places he had taken: The Duke ſends him a poſitive Command not to loſe one Foot of Ground, and that he ſhould be ſoon ſupplyed with what he wanted. Col. <hi>Lloyd,</hi> in obedience to the Duke's Command, was forced to divide his Men to Gariſon <hi>James-Town, Drumſnaw,</hi> and <hi>Abby Boyle,</hi> going himſelf to <hi>Sligo;</hi> ſending ſeveral times to <hi>Inniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killin</hi> for Ammunition, but none being ſent him, and the Duke not ſending Supplies early enough, our Men a while after (being divided in ſo ſmall Parties, and not capable of getting together) were beaten from all theſe Places by the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> our loſs of Men I confeſs was not great, yet we loſt one Lieut. <hi>Caſbcart,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Wiere,</hi> commonly called Leird <hi>Wiere,</hi> a valiant brave Fellow; and indeed his loſs was much lamented, for we had not a more forward Man amongſt us.</p>
            <p>The Duke after ſent a Detachment of Horſe, together with Col. <hi>Winn</hi>'s Dragoons, and ſome. Foot and Granadiers, under the Command of Coll. <hi>Ruſſel</hi> to reinforce <hi>Sligo;</hi> but Col. <hi>Sarafield</hi> making as good haſte back as he had made away, came up to <hi>Sligo</hi> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the Party ſent by the Duke was able to get that length: Col. <hi>Ruſſel</hi> who had Authority to Command in Chief at <hi>Sligo,</hi> with ſome few came in there late, the Night e're <hi>Sarsfield</hi> came; our Men drew out in the Morning to meet him, what of them were there, but they being ſo ſmall a Number, and wanting Ammunition, <hi>Sarsfield</hi> with an overpowring Party, being at leaſt ten to one, fell in with them, and beat them back into Town.</p>
            <p>Our Horſe were forced to retreat to <hi>Balliſhannon,</hi> our Foot got into the Fort of <hi>Sligo,</hi> Maj. <hi>Woodes</hi> having ſaved a ſmall Cask of Powder for the laſt Extremity, which he brought into the Fort with him; they held out three Days, killing abundance of the Enemy, ſallying out, and bringing in Proviſions for themſelves by Force, while at laſt they had what Conditions deſired; then they ſurrendred, marching out with Drums beating, Colours flying, Arms loaded, light Matches, and every Man took along with him what he had; Col. <hi>Sarsfield</hi> treated the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers very kindly with a Dinner, performing his Articles fully, ſo ſent them ſafe to <hi>Balliſhannon,</hi> and here ended the Actions of <hi>Inniskillin</hi>-men.</p>
            <p>I know I might have enlarged this Diſcourſe in ſeveral Places, and upon ſeveral Occaſions, but here you have a Brief of all that happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with a great deal of Sincerity and Truth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97788:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
